<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>multiple detachments | ZDEM官网</title>
    <link>https://geovbox.com/tag/multiple-detachments/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geovbox.com/tag/multiple-detachments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>multiple detachments</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>zh-Hans</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geovbox.com/media/icon_hua235b20c26de23a006d4e436991121ab_912_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>multiple detachments</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/tag/multiple-detachments/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Salt Thickness on the Structural Deformation of Foreland Fold-and-Thrust Belt in the Kuqa Depression</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210824/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210824/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;下载：&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.655173&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Li C, Yin H, Wu Z, Zhou P, Wang W, Ren R, Guan S, Li X, Luo H and Jia D (2021) Effects of Salt Thickness on the Structural Deformation of Foreland Fold-and-Thrust Belt in the Kuqa Depression, Tarim Basin: Insights From Discrete Element Models. Front. Earth Sci. 9:655173.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effects of Salt Thickness on the Structural Deformation of Foreland Fold-and-Thrust Belt in the Kuqa Depression, Tarim Basin: Insights From Discrete Element Models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changsheng Li&lt;sup&gt;1,2,3&lt;/sup&gt;, Hongwei Yin&lt;sup&gt;3*&lt;/sup&gt;, Zhenyun Wu&lt;sup&gt;1,2*&lt;/sup&gt;, Peng Zhou&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;, Wei Wang&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, Rong Ren&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;, Shuwei Guan&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;, Xiangyun Li&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;, Haoyu Luo&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; and Dong Jia&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State Key Laboratory of Nuclear Resources and Environment, East China University of Technology, Nanchang, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Sciences, East China University of Technology, Nanchang, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Sciences and Engineering, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resource Exploration Office, Tarim Oilfield Branch Company, PetroChina, Korla, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PetroChina Research Institute of Petroleum Exploration and Development, Beijing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Institute of Petroleum Exploration and Development, Tarim Oilfield Branch Company, PetroChina, Korla, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The salt layer is critical for the structural deformation in the salt-bearing fold-and-thrust system, which not only acts as the efficient décollement layer but also flows to form salt tectonics. Kuqa Depression has a well-preserved thin-skinned fold-and-thrust system with the salt layer as the décollement. To investigate the effects of salt thickness on the structural deformation in the Kuqa Depression, three discrete element models with different salt thicknesses were constructed. The experiment without salt was controlled by several basal décollement dominant faults, forming several imbricate sheets. The experiments with salt developed the decoupled deformation with the salt layer as the upper décollement (subsalt, intrasalt, and suprasalt), significantly similar to the Kuqa Depression along the northern margin of Tarim Basin. Basal décollement dominant imbricated thrusts formed at the subsalt units, while the monoclinal structure formed at the suprasalt units. The decoupled deformation was also observed in the tectonic deformation graphics, distortional strain fields, and max shear stress fields. However, the salt layer was thickened in the thick salt model, and the salt thickness of the thin salt model varied slightly because the thin salt weakened the flowability of the salt. The lower max shear stress zone was easily formed in the distribution region of salt under the action of compression stress, which is conducive to the flow convergence of salt and the crumpled deformation of interlayer in salt. The results are well consistent with the natural characteristics of structural deformation in the Kuqa Depression. Our modeling result concerns the structural characteristics and evolution of salt-related structures and the effects of salt thickness on the structural deformation in the compressional stress field, which might be helpful for the investigations of salt-related structures in other salt-bearing fold-and-thrust belts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g005_huce5bcdf3e3dd616ff1b0a530bd7ac663_111266_d1d6f58af265117b010d9ee9d3bd3fe3.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g005_huce5bcdf3e3dd616ff1b0a530bd7ac663_111266_e2af737f1fe08dfd4ef4c3f7aa4da913.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g005_huce5bcdf3e3dd616ff1b0a530bd7ac663_111266_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g005_huce5bcdf3e3dd616ff1b0a530bd7ac663_111266_d1d6f58af265117b010d9ee9d3bd3fe3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;608&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;FIGURE 5. Final deformations of three shortening experiments with different salt thicknesses after 12 km of shortening. A) Reference experiment. B) Experiment with thin salt (ca. 300 m). C) Experiment with thick salt (ca. 1,000 m). White and gray denote the subsalt layer. Red denotes the salt layer. Blue and gray denote the prekinematic layer. Violet and yellow denote the synkinematic layer. Bonds of assigned strengths (Table 2) were introduced at all interparticle contacts, except the synkinematic layer (violet and yellow) and salt layer (red). Dashed lines denote faults. The figures of each step are included in the Supplementary Material. &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g007_hu9959092851c17f4dd17a76e182574919_81840_79d3fedcb1c57724fdc2fb337ebf8c13.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g007_hu9959092851c17f4dd17a76e182574919_81840_3a9fb1e9c88f390f1b486e1a430eeb62.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g007_hu9959092851c17f4dd17a76e182574919_81840_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210824/feart-09-655173-g007_hu9959092851c17f4dd17a76e182574919_81840_79d3fedcb1c57724fdc2fb337ebf8c13.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;672&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;FIGURE 7. Max shear stress illustrated after 12 km of shortening. A) Reference experiment. B) Experiment with thin salt (ca. 300 m). C) Experiment with thick salt (ca. 1,000 m). The final structure of each series is superimposed by plotting regions of high distortional strain (i.e., the absolute value is greater than 4.8 in Figure 6) in black. Dashed lines denote faults. The areas that are trapped by the white solid line denote the salt. The figures of max shear stress for each step are included in the Supplementary Material.&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors would like to thank Julia K. Morgan and Thomas Fournier for generously sharing their postprocessing scripts and algorithms, which have been used to process and display the model outputs presented here. HY would like to thank Prof. Morgan for generously sharing her discrete element code RICEBAL (v. 5.1, modified from Peter Cundall’s TRUBAL v. 1.51) and Rice University for hosting his collaborative visit in 2009, providing him with the opportunity to further develop his knowledge of DEM and geomechanics principles and learn the capabilities of these methods. The authors also would like to thank Wenqiao XU for the fruitful discussions on this manuscript. The authors are grateful for thoughtful reviews by two reviewers, which resulted in significant improvements in this paper. The authors acknowledge Beijing PARATERA Tech CO., Ltd. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://paratera.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://paratera.com&lt;/a&gt;) for providing HPC resources that have contributed to the research results reported within this paper. Data used in this paper and the discrete element software ZDEM will be available online at &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com&lt;/a&gt;, and more examples are given on this website. Modeling results and information can be obtained by contacting CL at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:lichangsheng@ecut.edu.cn&#34;&gt;lichangsheng@ecut.edu.cn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;supplementary-material&#34;&gt;Supplementary Material&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/feart.2021.655173/full#supplementary-material&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/feart.2021.655173/full#supplementary-material&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>川西北双层滑脱体系构造变形过程离散元数值模拟</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;本文主要揭示双滑脱层模型在剥蚀和挤压条件下的构造演化过程。从腹陆端到挤压前缘，依次形成堆垛构造、被动顶板构造等，揭露
埋藏深部的隐伏薄皮构造样式，重塑新生代以来川西北剥蚀和挤压条件下的演化过程 &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-xu2021&#34;&gt;(Xu et al.,2021)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-xu2021&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
[Xu, W., Yin, H., Jia, D., **Li, C.**, Wang, W., Yang, G., He, W., Chen, Z., Ren, R., 2021. Structural Features and Evolution of the Northwestern Sichuan Basin: Insights From Discrete Numerical Simulations. Frontiers in Earth Science, 9:653395.](https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.653395) 
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural features and evolution of the northwestern Sichuan Basin Insights from discrete numerical simulations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenqiao Xu&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Hongwei Yin&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;*, Dong Jia&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Changsheng Li&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Wei Wang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Gengxiong Yang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,
Wanhui He&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Zhuxin Chen&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and Rong Ren&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Science and Engineering, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Science, East China University of Technology, Nanchang, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Institute of Petroleum Exploration and Development, Beijing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The northwestern Sichuan Basin has experienced Meso-Cenozoic intracontinental compressional tectonic processes and formed multi-detachment stratigraphic distribution of foreland basins and fold-thrust belts, which have caused complicated structural deformations in the deep buried layers. Rapid uplift with accelerated erosion and two sets of detachments in the Lower Triassic and Lower Cambrian controlled the multilevel deformation structure. We conducted discrete numerical simulations with double weak detachments and erosion under extrusion conditions in order to examine the mechanics and kinematics of the frontal piedmont zones of the NW Sichuan Basin. The following findings were made. (1) With continuous compression, the weak detachments promoted the decoupled and ladder-like deformation of the thrust belt, where the deformation above the slip layer extended further than it did below it. Rapid uplift and erosion at the thrust front contributed to the formation of a passive roof fault and a monocline in the upper layer, a series of forward and backward thin-skinned thrust-buried structures in the middle layer sandwiched between two weak detachments and stacking structures in the lower layer. (2) Erosion effectively prevents the deformation from propagating above the upper detachment, but can advance a horizontal transition in the deformation style generated within the middle brittle layer: from oblique and tight fault propagation folds to symmetrical, wide, and gentle detachment folds. (3) The model results consistent with tectonic deformation in the NW Sichuan Basin indicate a possible evolutionary mechanism under compression. There is hierarchical deformation of uncoordinated contraction controlled by the Lower Triassic and Early Cambrian weak layers, with the characteristics of the shallow monocline, the middle thin-skinned thrusts, and the deeper basement-involved folds. Continuous compression contributed a sequential pattern of steps as a whole, from the frontal piedmont zones to the foreland basin, autochthonous stacking thrusts, and the huge buried structure in the NW Sichuan Basin. During the Himalayan period, syntectonic erosion along with the uplifted thrust front maintained the development of a passive-roof duplex and a huge forward buried structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_b1f2e6b31556fe2dc3330c14e4ce11a0.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_8d004183b66203d9b6454a607446cb19.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_b1f2e6b31556fe2dc3330c14e4ce11a0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;567&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Modeled progress with two detachments due to the left-wall displacement &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_f4bc28b276feeb5d18b94ffeae5720fd.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_4d087576b96504b498433da025f941bb.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_f4bc28b276feeb5d18b94ffeae5720fd.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;569&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Modeled progress with two detachments and erosions due to the left-wall displacement&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_55290ad45df27a6e348506e07a0e9457.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_f0d4c75268a110c7c6ecb43e41bdcd6f.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_55290ad45df27a6e348506e07a0e9457.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;342&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Comparison of the slope angle versus shortening for the two models&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
