<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>马皓然 | ZDEM官网</title>
    <link>https://geovbox.com/authors/%E9%A9%AC%E7%9A%93%E7%84%B6/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geovbox.com/authors/%E9%A9%AC%E7%9A%93%E7%84%B6/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>马皓然</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>zh-Hans</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geovbox.com/media/icon_hua235b20c26de23a006d4e436991121ab_912_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>马皓然</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/authors/%E9%A9%AC%E7%9A%93%E7%84%B6/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>四川盆地威远背斜诱发地震的构造控制机理(Tectonics)</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;本文VBOX(ZDEM)实验脚本下载：&lt;/strong&gt;
The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本文研究了四川盆地威远背斜地区的构造对诱发地震的控制作用。通过地震解释、离散元数值模拟（DEM）和三维建模，探讨了威远背斜的结构与力学演化及其与水力压裂（HF）诱发地震的关系。研究发现，威远背斜的形成与基底卷入构造楔体密切相关，该结构由深部前冲断层和反向逆冲断层（BT）组成。在沉积盖层中，发育了密集的小位移逆冲断层，连接了志留系页岩滑脱层和寒武系滑脱层，促进了流体压力的向下扩散。研究结果表明，威远区块的诱发地震主要受控于两类构造：一类是与基底卷入构造楔相关的反向逆冲断层，其引发了2019年威远M  5.4地震等M&amp;gt;4的中强地震；另一类是沉积盖层中的页岩滑脱层，其与密集的逆冲断层共同作用，导致了M&amp;lt;4的小型地震。离散元模拟揭示了该区域基底卷入构造的形成过程及其对地震活动的控制机制，而三维结构模型进一步验证了地震与断层结构的空间关联性。这些发现为理解挤压环境下水力压裂诱发地震的机制提供了新视角，并对四川盆地及其他类似地质背景区域的页岩气开发中的地震风险评估具有重要启示。研究强调了识别基底断层结构和滑脱层分布对预防诱发地震的关键作用 &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Ma&amp;amp;Wang2025&#34;&gt;(Ma &amp;amp; Wang, 2025)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Ma&amp;Wang2025&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma, H., &amp;amp; Wang, M. (2025). Structural control of induced seismicity in the Weiyuan anticline, southwestern Sichuan foreland thrust belt, China. Tectonics, 44, e2024TC008617. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024TC008617&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024TC008617&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural Control of Induced Seismicity in the Weiyuan Anticline, Southwestern Sichuan Foreland Thrust Belt, China&lt;br&gt;
四川盆地威远背斜诱发地震的构造控制机理&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haoran Ma, Maomao Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institute of Tectonics and Geophysics, College of Oceanography, Hohai University, Nanjing, China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, the development of shale gas in the southwestern Sichuan foreland thrust belt, China, has led to a significant increase in induced seismicity, including one of the world&amp;rsquo;s largest hydraulic fracturing (HF)‐related induced earthquake (ML 5.4), occurring in the Weiyuan anticline. Here, we investigated the structural and mechanical evolution of the Weiyuan anticline and its relationship with HF‐induced earthquakes using seismic interpretation, the discrete‐element method (DEM), and three‐dimensional structural modeling. Interpretation of the seismic reflection profiles revealed a basement‐involved wedge structure and two west‐dipping multi‐bending thrust ramps in the basement. East of the Weiyuan anticline, extensive small‐ displacement thrust faults developed between the Cambrian and Silurian shale detachments in the sedimentary cover. DEM simulation showed that the structural wedge formed by the underlying blind thrust ramp and back thrust (BT) controlled the Weiyuan anticline formation. With increased shortening, the fault slip continued to propagate east of the Weiyuan anticline along the Cambrian detachment, leading to the development of
extensive thrust faults. 3‐D structural modeling showed that M &amp;gt; 4 induced earthquakes were primarily located on a BT in the structural wedge, while M &amp;lt; 4 events were distributed along the hydro‐fractured Silurian shale and Cambrian detachment. Densely developed thrust faults in the sedimentary cover connect the overpressured Silurian shale to the Cambrian detachment, promoting the downward diffusion of fluid pressure and favoring micro‐small M &amp;lt; 4 induced seismic events. This study provides new insights into the seismic hazard assessment of HF development in fold‐and‐thrust belts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_2a59903f096d20c9d59583fa075358ee.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_419772da573ef495303ea9c8f5414984.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_2a59903f096d20c9d59583fa075358ee.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;759&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 1. Topography map of the Longmen Shan and Sichuan Basin with major faults and cities. The red line indicates the location of seismic reflection profile PQ-92 in Fig. 5. The white pentagrams represent the MS 5.4 Weiyuan, MS 6.0 Luxian, MS 6.0 and 5.3 Changning respectively. The seismicity records from 1970 to 2014, and 2014 to 2020 are distinguished with grey and yellow circles, respectively. The earthquake data were obtained from the China Earthquake Networks Center, http://www.ceic.ac.cn/history in Chinese. 
 &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_9ee2da63c0652964b8549b278cfff7b0.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_e71bb18d7f0da8a52e53d01e22ae42c2.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_9ee2da63c0652964b8549b278cfff7b0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;642&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 5. (a) Structural interpretation of seismic reflection profile PQ-92 across the region of the Weiyuan to Dengjingguan anticlines, with wells K7 and WH101 constraining the horizons, are shown. (b) Restoration results of deformed horizons from Weiyuan to Dengjingguan anticlines. The shortening of the base of the Jurassic layer in a representative structural profile is 2.5 km. The Cenozoic sedimentary strata within this area in the profile are absent. The profile is shown at 2X vertical exaggeration. BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_011109828394052fcde16a8dc7989739.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_d3e2ee83195a933217c15251a90ef9fc.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_011109828394052fcde16a8dc7989739.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;666&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 6. Schematic representation of the experimental setup. (a) The initial model setup contained homogeneous mechanical properties. (b) The contractional wedge model setup contained two-level  basal detachments and three detachments in sedimentary cover, the wedge point occurs within the basement. (c) The shallow thrust ramp merged with an east-dipping detachment fault at the wedge point. BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_e84958987d99ce4d802178b8163eeebb.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_931e0c6e5091cd6e68dd20c7a62be3f9.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_e84958987d99ce4d802178b8163eeebb.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 7. Progressive evolution observed in homogeneous model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). F1–F5 denote thrust faults in the order of their formation. DTR: deep thrust ramp.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_782a0f031b03ad7dce3f78c445130c51.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_be31fff8ac280e4fb345139a3e491659.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_782a0f031b03ad7dce3f78c445130c51.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 8. Progressive evolution observed in contractional wedge model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). BT: back thrust; FT: fore thrust; STR: shallow thrust ramp; DTR: deep thrust ramp; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_269ddff8ab5282f7c559b25850a8fdfa.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_4b14001958f31d07afbcfcf171db921a.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_269ddff8ab5282f7c559b25850a8fdfa.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 10. Progressive evolution observed in the partitioned slipping wedge model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; STR: shallow thrust ramp; DTR: deep thrust ramp; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_7fa3f11bf73871bfdcb601cd2a67229d.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_df695b665a1adfef3fe56307d3b2572e.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_7fa3f11bf73871bfdcb601cd2a67229d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;464&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 11. Comparison between the structural cross-section of the Weiyuan to Kongtan anticlines and the result of the partitioned slipping wedge model. (a) Interpreted seismic profile in Figure 5. (b, c) The result of the partitioned slipping model when the shortening amount is 16 km, graph with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata (b), graph only with distortional strains (c). BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; D2: lower Silurian detachment; D3: mid-upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with structural interpretation, DEM simulations, and 3-D modeling, this study revealed the structure, kinematics, and mechanical evolution of a preexisting basement-involved structural wedge beneath the Weiyuan anticline and multiple detachments of the sedimentary cover in the southwestern Sichuan foreland fold-and-thrust belt, China, and discussed their influences on induced seismicity. Based on our study results, the following conclusions were drawn:
(1)The Weiyuan anticline is formed by a preexisting basement-involved contractional wedge consisting of a basal thrust ramp and a back thrust fault. East of the Weiyuan limb, the fault slip continued to propagate along the Cambrian detachment, contributing to the development of extensive low-displacement thrusts that cut through the Silurian shale detachment.
(2) The earthquakes induced in the Weiyuan block were primarily controlled by preexisting compressional basement-involved thrust structures and multi-level detachments in the sedimentary cover. The largest induced earthquake (2019 ML 5.2 event), along with other M &amp;gt; 4 earthquakes, occurred on BT within the basement-involved wedge structure.
(3) In the sedimentary cover, induced earthquakes (M &amp;lt; 4) primarily occurred between the Silurian shale and the middle–upper Cambrian shale detachments. Densely developed thrust faults connect the high-pore-pressure Silurian shale with Cambrian shale detachment, promoting the downward diffusion of pore pressure, which enhances the occurrence of induced earthquakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Editor‐in‐Chief Taylor Schildgen, Associate Editor Judith Hubbard, reviewer Andreas Plesch, and one anonymous reviewer for their comments and suggestions.This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (42172232 and 41702202) and National Key R&amp;amp;D Program of China (2021YFC3000604). Numerical simulations were performed on the discrete element modeling software VBOX (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geovbox.com/en%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;www.geovbox.com/en)&lt;/a&gt;. The authors thank Prof. Julia Morgan from Rice University for generously sharing her discrete element code (RICEBAL v5.4) and post-processing scripts and algorithms, which have been used to process and display the model outputs presented in our modeling. The numerical simulation of this study is performed on the computing facilities in the High-Performance Computing Center (HPCC) of Nanjing University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-availability-statement&#34;&gt;Data Availability Statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used VBOX version 2.1 ( &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Li2021&#34;&gt;Li et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt; ; &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com/en/&lt;/a&gt;) for the discrete-element method (DEM) numerical simulations. The web site &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com/en/&lt;/a&gt; provides manual and tutorial, examples, and references for VBOX version 2.1. The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/)&lt;/a&gt;. The relocated seismicity data used in this study is provided by &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Zi2023&#34;&gt;Zi et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;. The seismic reflection data, drilling wells, and structural maps were provided courtesy of the Southwest Oil and Gas Field Company, PetroChina. They cannot be released to the public. 3D models after time to depth conversion, including Middle-Upper Cambrian detachment, Lower Silurian detachment, and main faults, can also be obtained from Open Science Framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Li2021&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Li, C., Yin, H., Wu, C., Zhang, Y., Zhang, J., Wu, Z., et al. (2021). Calibration of the Discrete Element Method and Modeling of Shortening Experiments . Frontiers in Earth Science, 9(May),1–12. 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.636512&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.636512&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Zi2023&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Zi, J., Yang, H., Su, J., &amp; Chen, L. (2023). Structural constraints of induced earthquakes in the Weiyuan Shale Gas Field revealed by high-resolution body-wave tomography and earthquake relocation [Dataset]. Tectonophysics, 864(June), 230007. 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2023.230007&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2023.230007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>边缘海盆地断层差异演化成因的数值模拟：以西湖凹陷平北斜坡带为例（海洋地质与第四纪地质）</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;本文通过离散元数值模拟，模拟陆倾和海倾断层的形成及演化，以探讨断层几何发育特征的控制因素，为东海盆地构造演化机制及边缘海盆地的形成提供了思路和理论依据&lt;a href=&#34;#refer-qu2024&#34;&gt;(马皓然等,2024)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-ma2024&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kns.cnki.net/kcms2/article/abstract?v=FqYZq-Q0wRQbYEmrDX8Mje95BMn_IPljoXMr0YcRIfyJ1IlbvIoNObYw-CP0JywPXVbQn7kkFLk4V50vOx_n1IQ6hfgsz_6iwt6NLSyQDXui7-EYgBwg0DTWZZnfCf94zdfADO88tHkG-JH5JL8v_aHlCTlvFu8NogMJqpOCjrQ=&amp;amp;uniplatform=NZKPT&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;马皓然,苏金宝,王毛毛,等.边缘海盆地断层差异演化成因的数值模拟：以西湖凹陷平北斜坡带为例[J].海洋地质与第四纪地质,&lt;strong&gt;2024&lt;/strong&gt;,44(01):81-95.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;边缘海盆地断层差异演化成因的数值模拟：以西湖凹陷平北斜坡带为例&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;马皓然&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;，苏金宝&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;，王毛毛&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;，任培罡&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;，谈明轩&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;河海大学海洋学院，南京 210098&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;中石化华东石油工程有限公司科技发展分公司，南京 210098&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;东海陆架盆地中生代以来的成盆过程中，发育了大量陆倾控盆断裂，其发育模式与形成演化与东亚其他边缘海盆地差异明显。前人关注东海陆架盆地迁移特征，而忽略了断层差异演化的形成机制，对断层发育过程控制因素缺少深入研究。西湖凹陷平北斜坡带北部为海倾断层组成的断阶区，南部为陆倾断层组成的半地堑区，断裂差异演化指示着东海陆架盆地的成盆过程。本文通过离散元数值模拟，模拟陆倾和海倾断层的形成及演化，以探讨断层几何发育特征的控制因素。结果表明，岩性差异对斜坡带断层演化有较大影响，较高抗剪强度岩层破裂易产生陆倾控盆断裂，而低抗剪强度岩石则易形成向海倾断层。应力作用方向是区域差异演化的重要控制因素，岩石强度相同，应力作用方向相反时，断层倾向相反。盆地形成过程中发育众多凹陷斜坡，但坡度不是断层差异演化的主导因素。平北斜坡带和边缘海盆地的差异演化可能是由基底强度差异或应力方向差异导致的。本文利用离散元数值模拟平北斜坡带断裂差异演化过程，为东海盆地构造演化机制及边缘海盆地的形成提供了思路和理论依据。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_08da7e6950dc8bf22f397aea105ae653.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_c2c6dd650c45e1c23410fea55b25de60.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_08da7e6950dc8bf22f397aea105ae653.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图5 离散元数值模拟的模型边界条件&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_7d2f2f5769469721cd0a7edce3837c2a.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_a5659c07ceab02e2875017c45bbf4861.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_9830358d05bd3cb6516fed38c182e4d0.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_7d2f2f5769469721cd0a7edce3837c2a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;647&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图6 模型1构造变形、体积应变及断层断距统计&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_d49cad3d9c9c6f607b9e0f79a7f2f778.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_77d8ef681bedb49e8dc15e48fb3a84d1.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_c66394e089a1068486f4d0e63fd7dab9.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_d49cad3d9c9c6f607b9e0f79a7f2f778.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;636&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图7 模型2构造变形、体积应变及断层断距统计&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_816316b76d379207c9dc3f654beb1879.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_d58c9d795533f7b30e5f68c8f3067176.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_ab0fe22d4387d546c0a5b37bfe024bba.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_816316b76d379207c9dc3f654beb1879.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;638&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图8 模型3 构造变形、体积应变及断层断距统计&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE9%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B4%E6%9E%84%E9%80%A0%E5%8F%98%E5%BD%A2%E4%B8%8E%E4%BD%93%E7%A7%AF%E5%BA%94%E5%8F%98_hu73f2bc597992a69caf19b84b8dc1e1c5_190351_dace47bc0be7125cbde7173a43074247.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE9%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B4%E6%9E%84%E9%80%A0%E5%8F%98%E5%BD%A2%E4%B8%8E%E4%BD%93%E7%A7%AF%E5%BA%94%E5%8F%98_hu73f2bc597992a69caf19b84b8dc1e1c5_190351_befad4e4853792c7649fe71d3996e3e0.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE9%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B4%E6%9E%84%E9%80%A0%E5%8F%98%E5%BD%A2%E4%B8%8E%E4%BD%93%E7%A7%AF%E5%BA%94%E5%8F%98_hu73f2bc597992a69caf19b84b8dc1e1c5_190351_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE9%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B4%E6%9E%84%E9%80%A0%E5%8F%98%E5%BD%A2%E4%B8%8E%E4%BD%93%E7%A7%AF%E5%BA%94%E5%8F%98_hu73f2bc597992a69caf19b84b8dc1e1c5_190351_dace47bc0be7125cbde7173a43074247.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;300&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图9 模型4构造变形与体积应变&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_e34bd72731c117573303b2bdab75a4c9.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_349f0e8d9e7183aacd8105b2524a01e4.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_73ae9550489ccb35c3d8b0db918e1b25.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_e34bd72731c117573303b2bdab75a4c9.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;645&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图10 模型5构造变形、体积应变及断层断距统计&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;结论&#34;&gt;结论&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;岩石强度与应力方向是影响断层倾向变化的主要因素，高强度岩石破裂产生与伸展方向相反的断层，低强度岩石破裂产生与伸展方向同向的断层。相同强度的岩石在相反方向的应力影响下，产生的主断层倾向完全相反。基岩表面坡度和应力作用位置不是断层差异演化的主导因素。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;中国东部边缘海盆地差异演化可能受基底强度和应力方向差异控制。平北斜坡带南部和北部断层差异演化可能是由基岩强度差异引起的，或是应力方向差异导致的。东海陆架盆地的陆倾控盆断层可能是向海盆的伸展应力导致的，而南海陆缘盆地的断层发育可能是其基底在不同的应力方向共同作用下的结果。岩性和应力方向差异可能导致盆地差异演化，从而影响同时期油气运聚，但仍需进一步研究二者的相关性。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;致谢&#34;&gt;致谢&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本文的数值计算是在南京大学高性能计算中心的计算集群上完成的, 数值模拟实验使用东华理工大学李长圣博士研发的离散元数值模拟软件完成。文中采用的应变计算代码修改自莱斯大学 Julia K Morgan 和 Thomas Fournier 的脚本，在此表示感谢。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
