<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>王毛毛 | ZDEM官网</title>
    <link>https://geovbox.com/authors/%E7%8E%8B%E6%AF%9B%E6%AF%9B/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geovbox.com/authors/%E7%8E%8B%E6%AF%9B%E6%AF%9B/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>王毛毛</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>zh-Hans</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geovbox.com/media/icon_hua235b20c26de23a006d4e436991121ab_912_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>王毛毛</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/authors/%E7%8E%8B%E6%AF%9B%E6%AF%9B/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>多边形断层系统（PFSs）俯冲对增生楔构造变形与浅部慢滑移事件（SSEs）的影响（Science Advances）</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/</guid>
      <description>















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34;
           src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/sciadv.adu4227_movie_s7.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;600px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2025年7月5日，河海大学海洋学院王毛毛教授课题组及其合作者在国际顶尖综合类期刊《Science Advances》发表了题为“Effects of incoming polygonal fault systems on subduction zone and slow slip behavior”的研究论文，揭示了西太平洋新西兰Hikurangi俯冲带与日本南海海槽中多边形断层系统（PFSs）俯冲对增生楔构造变形与浅部慢滑移事件（SSEs）的影响机制。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;俯冲带发生的大地震及其造成的海啸、海底滑坡等是全球海洋中最具破坏性的自然灾害类型。传统上认为俯冲界面断层主要通过两种方式吸收板块间的相对运动，分别为：1）粘滑，即周期性的地震快速滑动；2）蠕滑，即与板块运动速率一致的稳态滑动。但近年来，测地学与地震学观测显示俯冲带还存在多种慢地震类型，包括慢滑移事件（slow slip events, SSEs）、低频地震（Low frequency earthquakes, LVEs）、甚低频地震（Very low frequency earthquake, VLVEs）、构造震颤（tectonic tremors）等。其中，SSEs表现为在俯冲界面周期性发生数厘米至数十厘米的断层滑动，每次持续时间超过数天、数月、甚至数年。SSEs可以通过增加相邻断层面的静态应力来触发俯冲界面的大地震，如日本海沟长达十年的SSEs被认为可能触发了2011年Mw 9.0日本东北地震，因此对其深入研究可能是预测俯冲带未来大地震的关键突破点。&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_403d63854616d98869c9cb530071dd70.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_2d88f29841d7eccc7d944c57b1ab4f41.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_403d63854616d98869c9cb530071dd70.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图1 西太平洋新西兰希库朗吉（Hikurangi）俯冲带地形、IODP 375航次钻位、NZ3D三维地震体以及2014年SSEs等分布&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;尽管SSEs在全球多个俯冲带已有大量观测，然而对于其形成机制仍不明确。在众多假设中，粗糙海底的俯冲以及俯冲界面断层带内的岩性非均质性被普遍认为是主要影响因素。历史记载与现代观测表明，新西兰希库朗吉和日本南海海槽俯冲带都曾发生大地震，并频繁出现浅部SSEs、tremors、VLFEs以及海啸等现象。海底大地测量显示，希库朗吉北缘和南海海槽的SSEs与VLFEs向上延伸至海底以下2公里，甚至可能一直延伸至海沟处（图1）。这是全球最浅且记录最为完整的SSEs，因此提供了绝佳的机遇来通过大洋科学钻探、地球物理探测、构造解析、数值模拟等手段来研究SSEs的本质机制与行为，及其与俯冲界面大地震之间的关系。最近的研究在南海和希库朗吉海槽等俯冲带的输入沉积序列中，发现了多边形断层系统（PFSs）。这些PFSs具有正断层位移性质、多边形结构和紧密间距特征，大多位于输入板块的原型滑脱层正上方。输入板块中发现的PFSs引发了关于其在巨型逆冲断层结构、水文地质及地震行为中作用的重要问题：这些PFSs在俯冲过程中是否会在增生楔内重新活化，以及是否会影响巨型逆冲断层的应变分配、几何粗糙度及物质非均质性？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;针对上述问题，研究人员结合国际大洋发现计划（IODP）372/375航次钻探结果、基于离散元数值模拟，结合Hikurangi边缘最新采集的三维地震反射数据体（NZ3D）、可控源大地电磁（HT-RESIST）数据解释，来研究输入板块的多边形断层系统（PFSs）在进入俯冲带后，对增生楔和板块边界巨型逆冲断层的运动学与力学影响。采用离散元方法（ZDEM）建立一系列对比模型，探究不同倾角与间距PFSs在增生楔中的断裂演化过程，最终评估其对增生楔构造演化及板块界面滑动性质的影响。三维地震解释证实紧邻巨型逆冲断层界面的PFSs能够被激活并沿构造走向逐渐演化成主逆冲断层（图2）。研究发现，希库朗吉和南海海槽来临板块中PFSs的典型断层倾角与DEM数值模拟揭示的最有利于激活的断层倾角范围一致（图3）。&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_42c6f4f9b080811534b0852fdf71b417.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_e2921867bd5cb6b9e05aca2d737b6447.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_42c6f4f9b080811534b0852fdf71b417.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;462&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图2 NZ3D地震数据体构造解译揭示了PFSs在增生楔底部的位置及其与主逆冲断层的空间关系&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;结合NZ3D三维地震速度模型以及大地电磁数据的对比表明，PFSs的重新活化可以为流体运移提供了双重通道效应：既可沿板块界面输送下部楔体的流体，也可导致滑脱层之下富含流体火山碎屑岩的瞬态渗漏。这些现象与楔体底部地层扰动以及剪切应力减弱等现象吻合，因此增强了沿巨型逆冲断层的几何不规则性、流体压力与应力分布的非均质性。综合这些发现表明，俯冲带输入板块中PFSs的激活与增生可能通过此前未被认识的机制，对俯冲带浅部多种慢地震现象的产生起到促进作用。&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_035f33ee79f131d6d819f836dfae2189.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_1bcc64cfd12ab8ef7a30b911bcdf8a4e.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_035f33ee79f131d6d819f836dfae2189.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;435&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;图3 DEM模拟PFSs增生过程的断层结构和最大剪应力场的统计数据对比&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;论文第一作者和通讯作者为河海大学海洋学院王毛毛教授，合作者包括新西兰国立水与大气研究所（NIWA）首席科学家Philip Barnes博士、美国德州大学奥斯汀分校Demian Saffer教授、夏威夷大学Gregory Moore教授等，以及河海大学海洋学院博士研究生马皓然、硕士研究生王明和河海大学海洋学院苏金宝教授等。该研究得到了国际大洋发现计划（IODP）、IODP中国办公室、国家自然科学基金项目（42172232）等支持。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;下载链接：&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-wang2025&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/epdf/10.1126/sciadv.adu4227&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Maomao Wang, Philip M. Barnes, Demian Saffer, Gregory F. Moore, Haoran Ma, Ming Wang, Jinbao Su (2025). Effects of incoming polygonal fault systems on subduction zone and slow slip behavior. Science Advances, 11(27), eadu4227.&lt;/a&gt; IF2025 = 12.5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effects of incoming polygonal fault systems on subduction zone and slow slip behavior&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maomao Wang&lt;sup&gt;1*&lt;/sup&gt;, Philip M. Barnes&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Demian Saffer&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, Gregory F. Moore&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;, Haoran Ma&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,   Ming Wang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Jinbao Su&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;College of Oceanography, hohai University, nanjing, Jiangsu, china.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;National in stitute of Water and Atmospheric Research, Wellington, new Zealand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University  of texas institute for Geophysics, Austin, tX, USA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Department of earth Sciences,  University of hawaii, honolulu, hi, USA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Correspondence to: Maomao Wang(&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:wangmm@hhu.edu.cn&#34;&gt;wangmm@hhu.edu.cn&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physical properties of subduction inputs profoundly influence megathrust slip behavior. Seismic data reveal  extensive polygonal fault systems (PFSs) in the input sequences of the Hikurangi Margin and Nankai Trough. The  mechanical and hydrological effects of these incoming PFSs on subduction zones are potentially substantial.  Here, we investigate their effects following transport into the accretionary wedge by integrating discrete- element  modeling with three- dimensional seismic interpretation. We find that the typical dips of the incoming PFSs over lap with modeled dips prone to reactivation and confirm that subducting PFSs can be reactivated and gradually  evolve into major thrust faults. Comparisons with electromagnetic data indicate that PFSs may provide conduits  for fluid leakage along the plate interface, coincide with disrupted strata and decreased shear stress, and enhance  geometric and stress heterogeneity along the megathrust. These suggest that PFSs may play a previously unrec ognized role in contributing to shallow slow earthquake phenomena in subduction zones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_403d63854616d98869c9cb530071dd70.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_2d88f29841d7eccc7d944c57b1ab4f41.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/Figure2_hu403e3a493c2ad32080e36ee44fff6513_327454_403d63854616d98869c9cb530071dd70.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Figure 2. Bathymetric map showing the location of the NZ3D seismic volume at the northern Hikurangi Margin.&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
 (A) Regional tectonics setting. (B) Blue lines with labels are seismic slip contours (cm) for the September to October 2014 SSes (12). White transparent rectangle demarks the location of the coherent depth slice at 5140 m shown in Fig. 4c. Red star shows the location of the 1947 tsunami earthquake. Yellow circles mark the locations of iOdP expeditions 372 and 375 drilling sites. the blue and purple thick lines show the locations of the sections in (d) and Fig. 10A, respectively. (C) lithostratigraphy for iOdP site U1520 (3, 24). Bidirectional arrows indicate that PFSs develop primarily in calcareous, clay- rich sediments of Unit iv. (D) Partial section of il 135 in nZ3d showing PFSs, seamounts, décollement, proto- décollement, and slow slip. mbsf, meters below seafloor.
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_42c6f4f9b080811534b0852fdf71b417.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_e2921867bd5cb6b9e05aca2d737b6447.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/Figure4_huf4cb04413d6655e6ef3da2479854e4c7_360630_42c6f4f9b080811534b0852fdf71b417.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;462&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Figure 4. Seismic profiles and coherence depth slice from the NZ3D reflection volume showing accreted PFSs and thrust faults in the Hikurangi Margin. &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
(A) Perspective view of the seismic profile (il 135) and coherence depth slice (5140 m) looking northwest. (B) enlarged panel from il 135 showing PFSs, the southern part of the Pāpaku thrust, and other faults. (C) coherence depth slice at 5140 m showing the distinct expression of PFSs in the pelagic unit within the accretionary wedge. (D) crossline 2075 showing the relationship between the lateral ramp of Pāpaku thrust and PFSs through which the thrust emerges. vertical exaggeration is 1.5:1.
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250709/sciadv.adu4227-f6_hu7d8496496add47ee55dd2709811685e3_744782_fea05e77ab86936070d17a1a362f88d7.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250709/sciadv.adu4227-f6_hu7d8496496add47ee55dd2709811685e3_744782_ca457958a3d8a4dd4af4d0b4d410e0f7.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250709/sciadv.adu4227-f6_hu7d8496496add47ee55dd2709811685e3_744782_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/sciadv.adu4227-f6_hu7d8496496add47ee55dd2709811685e3_744782_fea05e77ab86936070d17a1a362f88d7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Figure 6. Comparison of structural deformation without and with polygonal faults in accretionary wedges based on DEM simulation.&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
(A) Without polygonal faults and (B to D) with polygonal faults at dip angles of θ = 35°, 45°, and 55°, respectively. The red + blue and white + blue areas represent trench fill and pelagic sediment units, respectively. T1 to T6 represent the thrust faults generated sequentially during the deformation process. The deformation strain field is superimposed on the colored layers.
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_035f33ee79f131d6d819f836dfae2189.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_1bcc64cfd12ab8ef7a30b911bcdf8a4e.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250709/Figure7_hu6c8e0978fd3e310499ed4676cbd96ce3_183663_035f33ee79f131d6d819f836dfae2189.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;435&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Figure 7. Statistical data for modeled fault structures and maximum shear stresses field in the accretionary wedge. &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
(A) Probability density function of the subducting PFS fault dips calculated from seismic reflection data in hikurangi and nankai margins. the blue transparent regions of (A) to (c) represent the dip range (45° to 65°) that is most favorable for the reactivation of PFSs. (B and C) Quantity and proportion of fore- thrusts and back- thrusts faults formed in the deM Model i under various PFS fault dips. (D and E) distribution of maximum shear stresses within the wedges in the smooth reference model and the PFS- bearing model (fault dip, θ = 55°). Model shortening is 23 km.
&lt;h3 id=&#34;参考文献&#34;&gt;参考文献&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;限于篇幅，参考文献详见：Wang M, Barnes P M, Saffer D, et al. (2025). Effects of incoming polygonal fault systems on subduction zone and slow slip behavior. Science Advances, 11(27): eadu4227. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/epdf/10.1126/sciadv.adu4227&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/epdf/10.1126/sciadv.adu4227&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;转载自-httpswwwhhueducn20250705c166a305280pagehtm&#34;&gt;转载自 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hhu.edu.cn/2025/0705/c166a305280/page.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.hhu.edu.cn/2025/0705/c166a305280/page.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>四川盆地威远背斜诱发地震的构造控制机理(Tectonics)</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;本文VBOX(ZDEM)实验脚本下载：&lt;/strong&gt;
The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本文研究了四川盆地威远背斜地区的构造对诱发地震的控制作用。通过地震解释、离散元数值模拟（DEM）和三维建模，探讨了威远背斜的结构与力学演化及其与水力压裂（HF）诱发地震的关系。研究发现，威远背斜的形成与基底卷入构造楔体密切相关，该结构由深部前冲断层和反向逆冲断层（BT）组成。在沉积盖层中，发育了密集的小位移逆冲断层，连接了志留系页岩滑脱层和寒武系滑脱层，促进了流体压力的向下扩散。研究结果表明，威远区块的诱发地震主要受控于两类构造：一类是与基底卷入构造楔相关的反向逆冲断层，其引发了2019年威远M  5.4地震等M&amp;gt;4的中强地震；另一类是沉积盖层中的页岩滑脱层，其与密集的逆冲断层共同作用，导致了M&amp;lt;4的小型地震。离散元模拟揭示了该区域基底卷入构造的形成过程及其对地震活动的控制机制，而三维结构模型进一步验证了地震与断层结构的空间关联性。这些发现为理解挤压环境下水力压裂诱发地震的机制提供了新视角，并对四川盆地及其他类似地质背景区域的页岩气开发中的地震风险评估具有重要启示。研究强调了识别基底断层结构和滑脱层分布对预防诱发地震的关键作用 &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Ma&amp;amp;Wang2025&#34;&gt;(Ma &amp;amp; Wang, 2025)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Ma&amp;Wang2025&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma, H., &amp;amp; Wang, M. (2025). Structural control of induced seismicity in the Weiyuan anticline, southwestern Sichuan foreland thrust belt, China. Tectonics, 44, e2024TC008617. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024TC008617&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024TC008617&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural Control of Induced Seismicity in the Weiyuan Anticline, Southwestern Sichuan Foreland Thrust Belt, China&lt;br&gt;
四川盆地威远背斜诱发地震的构造控制机理&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haoran Ma, Maomao Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institute of Tectonics and Geophysics, College of Oceanography, Hohai University, Nanjing, China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, the development of shale gas in the southwestern Sichuan foreland thrust belt, China, has led to a significant increase in induced seismicity, including one of the world&amp;rsquo;s largest hydraulic fracturing (HF)‐related induced earthquake (ML 5.4), occurring in the Weiyuan anticline. Here, we investigated the structural and mechanical evolution of the Weiyuan anticline and its relationship with HF‐induced earthquakes using seismic interpretation, the discrete‐element method (DEM), and three‐dimensional structural modeling. Interpretation of the seismic reflection profiles revealed a basement‐involved wedge structure and two west‐dipping multi‐bending thrust ramps in the basement. East of the Weiyuan anticline, extensive small‐ displacement thrust faults developed between the Cambrian and Silurian shale detachments in the sedimentary cover. DEM simulation showed that the structural wedge formed by the underlying blind thrust ramp and back thrust (BT) controlled the Weiyuan anticline formation. With increased shortening, the fault slip continued to propagate east of the Weiyuan anticline along the Cambrian detachment, leading to the development of
extensive thrust faults. 3‐D structural modeling showed that M &amp;gt; 4 induced earthquakes were primarily located on a BT in the structural wedge, while M &amp;lt; 4 events were distributed along the hydro‐fractured Silurian shale and Cambrian detachment. Densely developed thrust faults in the sedimentary cover connect the overpressured Silurian shale to the Cambrian detachment, promoting the downward diffusion of fluid pressure and favoring micro‐small M &amp;lt; 4 induced seismic events. This study provides new insights into the seismic hazard assessment of HF development in fold‐and‐thrust belts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_2a59903f096d20c9d59583fa075358ee.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_419772da573ef495303ea9c8f5414984.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_2a59903f096d20c9d59583fa075358ee.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;759&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 1. Topography map of the Longmen Shan and Sichuan Basin with major faults and cities. The red line indicates the location of seismic reflection profile PQ-92 in Fig. 5. The white pentagrams represent the MS 5.4 Weiyuan, MS 6.0 Luxian, MS 6.0 and 5.3 Changning respectively. The seismicity records from 1970 to 2014, and 2014 to 2020 are distinguished with grey and yellow circles, respectively. The earthquake data were obtained from the China Earthquake Networks Center, http://www.ceic.ac.cn/history in Chinese. 
 &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_9ee2da63c0652964b8549b278cfff7b0.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_e71bb18d7f0da8a52e53d01e22ae42c2.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_9ee2da63c0652964b8549b278cfff7b0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;642&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 5. (a) Structural interpretation of seismic reflection profile PQ-92 across the region of the Weiyuan to Dengjingguan anticlines, with wells K7 and WH101 constraining the horizons, are shown. (b) Restoration results of deformed horizons from Weiyuan to Dengjingguan anticlines. The shortening of the base of the Jurassic layer in a representative structural profile is 2.5 km. The Cenozoic sedimentary strata within this area in the profile are absent. The profile is shown at 2X vertical exaggeration. BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_011109828394052fcde16a8dc7989739.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_d3e2ee83195a933217c15251a90ef9fc.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_011109828394052fcde16a8dc7989739.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;666&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 6. Schematic representation of the experimental setup. (a) The initial model setup contained homogeneous mechanical properties. (b) The contractional wedge model setup contained two-level  basal detachments and three detachments in sedimentary cover, the wedge point occurs within the basement. (c) The shallow thrust ramp merged with an east-dipping detachment fault at the wedge point. BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_e84958987d99ce4d802178b8163eeebb.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_931e0c6e5091cd6e68dd20c7a62be3f9.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_e84958987d99ce4d802178b8163eeebb.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 7. Progressive evolution observed in homogeneous model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). F1–F5 denote thrust faults in the order of their formation. DTR: deep thrust ramp.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_782a0f031b03ad7dce3f78c445130c51.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_be31fff8ac280e4fb345139a3e491659.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_782a0f031b03ad7dce3f78c445130c51.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 8. Progressive evolution observed in contractional wedge model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). BT: back thrust; FT: fore thrust; STR: shallow thrust ramp; DTR: deep thrust ramp; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_269ddff8ab5282f7c559b25850a8fdfa.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_4b14001958f31d07afbcfcf171db921a.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_269ddff8ab5282f7c559b25850a8fdfa.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 10. Progressive evolution observed in the partitioned slipping wedge model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; STR: shallow thrust ramp; DTR: deep thrust ramp; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_7fa3f11bf73871bfdcb601cd2a67229d.webp 400w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_df695b665a1adfef3fe56307d3b2572e.webp 760w,
               /blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_7fa3f11bf73871bfdcb601cd2a67229d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;464&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 11. Comparison between the structural cross-section of the Weiyuan to Kongtan anticlines and the result of the partitioned slipping wedge model. (a) Interpreted seismic profile in Figure 5. (b, c) The result of the partitioned slipping model when the shortening amount is 16 km, graph with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata (b), graph only with distortional strains (c). BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; D2: lower Silurian detachment; D3: mid-upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with structural interpretation, DEM simulations, and 3-D modeling, this study revealed the structure, kinematics, and mechanical evolution of a preexisting basement-involved structural wedge beneath the Weiyuan anticline and multiple detachments of the sedimentary cover in the southwestern Sichuan foreland fold-and-thrust belt, China, and discussed their influences on induced seismicity. Based on our study results, the following conclusions were drawn:
(1)The Weiyuan anticline is formed by a preexisting basement-involved contractional wedge consisting of a basal thrust ramp and a back thrust fault. East of the Weiyuan limb, the fault slip continued to propagate along the Cambrian detachment, contributing to the development of extensive low-displacement thrusts that cut through the Silurian shale detachment.
(2) The earthquakes induced in the Weiyuan block were primarily controlled by preexisting compressional basement-involved thrust structures and multi-level detachments in the sedimentary cover. The largest induced earthquake (2019 ML 5.2 event), along with other M &amp;gt; 4 earthquakes, occurred on BT within the basement-involved wedge structure.
(3) In the sedimentary cover, induced earthquakes (M &amp;lt; 4) primarily occurred between the Silurian shale and the middle–upper Cambrian shale detachments. Densely developed thrust faults connect the high-pore-pressure Silurian shale with Cambrian shale detachment, promoting the downward diffusion of pore pressure, which enhances the occurrence of induced earthquakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Editor‐in‐Chief Taylor Schildgen, Associate Editor Judith Hubbard, reviewer Andreas Plesch, and one anonymous reviewer for their comments and suggestions.This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (42172232 and 41702202) and National Key R&amp;amp;D Program of China (2021YFC3000604). Numerical simulations were performed on the discrete element modeling software VBOX (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geovbox.com/en%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;www.geovbox.com/en)&lt;/a&gt;. The authors thank Prof. Julia Morgan from Rice University for generously sharing her discrete element code (RICEBAL v5.4) and post-processing scripts and algorithms, which have been used to process and display the model outputs presented in our modeling. The numerical simulation of this study is performed on the computing facilities in the High-Performance Computing Center (HPCC) of Nanjing University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-availability-statement&#34;&gt;Data Availability Statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used VBOX version 2.1 ( &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Li2021&#34;&gt;Li et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt; ; &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com/en/&lt;/a&gt;) for the discrete-element method (DEM) numerical simulations. The web site &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com/en/&lt;/a&gt; provides manual and tutorial, examples, and references for VBOX version 2.1. The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/)&lt;/a&gt;. The relocated seismicity data used in this study is provided by &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Zi2023&#34;&gt;Zi et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;. The seismic reflection data, drilling wells, and structural maps were provided courtesy of the Southwest Oil and Gas Field Company, PetroChina. They cannot be released to the public. 3D models after time to depth conversion, including Middle-Upper Cambrian detachment, Lower Silurian detachment, and main faults, can also be obtained from Open Science Framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Li2021&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Li, C., Yin, H., Wu, C., Zhang, Y., Zhang, J., Wu, Z., et al. (2021). Calibration of the Discrete Element Method and Modeling of Shortening Experiments . Frontiers in Earth Science, 9(May),1–12. 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.636512&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.636512&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Zi2023&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Zi, J., Yang, H., Su, J., &amp; Chen, L. (2023). Structural constraints of induced earthquakes in the Weiyuan Shale Gas Field revealed by high-resolution body-wave tomography and earthquake relocation [Dataset]. Tectonophysics, 864(June), 230007. 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2023.230007&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2023.230007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>地表过程对龙门山褶皱冲断带应变分布及地震活动的影响：基于离散元模拟的认识(Tectonics)</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;本文VBOX(ZDEM)实验脚本下载：&lt;/strong&gt;
The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework (Model I-1, no surface processes, &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/tz2qg;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/tz2qg;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;gt; Model I-2, with surface processes, &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/pa9sy%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/pa9sy)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本文研究了位于青藏高原东缘的龙门山褶皱冲断带及其毗邻的川西前陆盆地的构造变形与地表过程的相互作用。利用离散元数值模拟的方法，研究了不同力学性质的滑脱层以及同构造侵蚀/沉积过程对龙门山和川西前陆盆地构造演化的影响。模拟结果显示：晚新生代的两期地表过程显著地影响着龙门山内陆及前陆地区的逆冲序列与应变局部化。在缺少地表过程的影响下，褶皱冲断带以“前展式”向前传播，而在有地表过程中则以“乱序式”（out-of-sequence）的逆冲方式。作者推断晚新生代以来，从四川盆地向西至青藏高原的大规模侵蚀作用传播的影响下，龙门山内陆演变为次临界状态。构造活动性后撤至高原的边缘，导致了龙门山的快速隆升并抑制了大量缩短变形传播至前陆盆地。前陆冲断带沿浅部滑脱层的稳定滑移导致前缘龙泉断层的形成和生长。这些结果解释了为何龙门山内陆冲断带和川西前陆冲断带现今同时处于地震活动状态的原因。该研究对活跃地表过程作用下的褶皱冲断带地震潜在活动性的研究提供了重要的启示&lt;a href=&#34;#refer-wang2022&#34;&gt;(Wang et al.,2022)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-wang2022&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wang, M., Wang, M., Feng, W., Yan, B., &amp;amp; Jia, D. (2022). Influence of surface processes on strain localization and seismic activity in the Longmen Shan fold-and-thrust belt: Insights from discrete-element modeling. &lt;strong&gt;Tectonics&lt;/strong&gt;, 41, e2022TC007515. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022TC007515&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022TC007515&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Influence of Surface Processes on Strain Localization and Seismic Activity in the Longmen Shan Fold-and-Thrust Belt: Insights From Discrete-Element Modeling&lt;br&gt;
地表过程对龙门山褶皱冲断带应变分布及地震活动的影响：基于离散元模拟的认识&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maomao Wang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,Ming Wang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,Wang Feng&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,Bing Yan&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,Dong Jia&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Institute of Tectonics and Geophysics, College of Oceanography, Hohai University, Nanjing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Sciences and Engineering, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We investigated interactions between structural deformation and surface processes in the Longmen Shan fold-and-thrust belt and the adjacent western Sichuan foreland basin (WSFB) in the eastern margin of the Tibetan Plateau. The discrete-element modeling (DEM) method was used to study the influences of the various mechanical properties of the detachments and syn-tectonic erosion/deposition on the structural evolution of the Longmen Shan and WSFB. DEM simulations demonstrated two stages of surface processes during the Late Cenozoic profoundly influenced thrusting sequences and strain localization in the hinterland and foreland portions of the Longmen Shan. Models indicate that the fold-and-thrust belt lacking surface processes propagate in a forward-breaking manner, whereas those with surface processes develop following an out-of-sequence thrusting pattern. We infer that large-scale erosion propagation from the Sichuan Basin westward to the Tibetan Plateau since Late Cenozoic caused the Longmen Shan hinterland to reach a subcritical wedge state. Tectonic activity retreats to the edge of Plateau, enhancing the rapid uplift of the Longmen Shan and inhibiting the propagation of substantial shortening deformation to the foreland basin. The foreland thrust belt slides stably along the shallow detachment, causing the initiation and growth of the Longquan fault in the leading front. These results explain why both the Longmen Shan hinterland and the western Sichuan foreland thrust belts are currently in a state of simultaneous seismic activity. Our findings offer important implications regarding the seismic potentials of other fold-and-thrust belts that interact with dynamic surface processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0001-m_hu6e47567c19fe7e019acef287476481c2_1909815_b5759661a5141cdb2475d33b2cb74d12.webp 400w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0001-m_hu6e47567c19fe7e019acef287476481c2_1909815_a61fc24d396ba38300abd0e5b4220c99.webp 760w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0001-m_hu6e47567c19fe7e019acef287476481c2_1909815_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0001-m_hu6e47567c19fe7e019acef287476481c2_1909815_b5759661a5141cdb2475d33b2cb74d12.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 1. Geological map of the eastern Tibetan Plateau showing the focal mechanisms of the 2008 Mw 7.9 Wenchuan earthquake, the 2013 Mw 6.6 Lushan earthquake, and the 2020 Ms 5.1 Qingbaijiang earthquake. The red lines represent surface ruptures of the 2008 Wenchuan earthquake ([Liu-Zeng et al., 2009](#refer-Liu-Zeng2009); [Xu et al., 2009](#refer-Xu2009)). The gray rectangles represent the age of previous published low-temperature thermochronology data, from ([E. Wang et al., 2012](#refer-Wang2012) )&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; and ([Richardson et al., 2008](#refer-Richardson2008))&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;. The brown lines represent the structural profiles in the study area, where profile (a–c) is shown in Figures 5a–5c, respectively. LQF: Longquan Fault; PGT: Pengguan Thrust; RFBT: Range Front Blind Thrust; WLF, Wulong Thrust; WLT: Wenchuan–Maowen Fault; XPT: Xiongpo Thrust; YBT: Yingxiu–Beichuan Thrust.
 &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0006-m_hudc9d6188a4897d745c394d359f80ff8a_193460_16dcc8e7c9d52de647a887b2d9ac3926.webp 400w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0006-m_hudc9d6188a4897d745c394d359f80ff8a_193460_7fabd3ea757f0c53607bdef83c1d7041.webp 760w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0006-m_hudc9d6188a4897d745c394d359f80ff8a_193460_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_2.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0006-m_hudc9d6188a4897d745c394d359f80ff8a_193460_16dcc8e7c9d52de647a887b2d9ac3926.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;247&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 6. (a) Representative structural profile a (see location in Figure 1) in the central segment of the Longmen Shan fold-and-thrust belt (Jia et al., 2010). (b) Restoration results of deformed horizons in foreland region of structural profile (a) The shortening of the base of Jurassic layer in foreland region is 13.3 km. The Cenozoic sedimentary strata within hinterland of the Longmen Shan in this profile are absent.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0008-m_hu9e51719c821a31c8b0a478752f3ca8c6_384658_ef86a1c06c29e41584673cdce958a3b4.webp 400w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0008-m_hu9e51719c821a31c8b0a478752f3ca8c6_384658_f8437e00100ec09ba465ace4fd0caab0.webp 760w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0008-m_hu9e51719c821a31c8b0a478752f3ca8c6_384658_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_2.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0008-m_hu9e51719c821a31c8b0a478752f3ca8c6_384658_ef86a1c06c29e41584673cdce958a3b4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;545&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 8. Schematic representation of the experimental setup. (a) The initial model setup contained two-level detachments with differential mechanical strengths. (b) When simulating the surface processes in the first stage of Model I-2, the eroded materials from the hinterland were deposited sequentially in the foreland. c) When simulating the surface processes in the second stage of Model I-2, surface erosion occurred throughout the wedge, and materials were transported from the system. The stages of b and c of Model I-2 are not to scale.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0009-m_hu52f33272bef0373b7ce3abc384379469_1018390_72d211fccc940f1c28c3b321c21a70fa.webp 400w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0009-m_hu52f33272bef0373b7ce3abc384379469_1018390_f98470a5d84eb615a040f6e637fc6aec.webp 760w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0009-m_hu52f33272bef0373b7ce3abc384379469_1018390_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0009-m_hu52f33272bef0373b7ce3abc384379469_1018390_72d211fccc940f1c28c3b321c21a70fa.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 9. The progressive evolution observed in Model I-1 (conducted with five stages and no surface processes), with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(e) The results of Model I-1 at total shortenings of 10 km (a), 15 km (b), 24 km (c), 30 km (d), or 35 km (e). T1–T7 denote thrust faults in the order of their formation. RFBT, Range Front blind thrust.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0010-m_hueb618714f7a1bb1123e4798edf35ac39_1065171_0458118cd182f8b58c16e7c03f53edb4.webp 400w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0010-m_hueb618714f7a1bb1123e4798edf35ac39_1065171_1e22ad9b02f235cee772725ac0e9917b.webp 760w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0010-m_hueb618714f7a1bb1123e4798edf35ac39_1065171_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0010-m_hueb618714f7a1bb1123e4798edf35ac39_1065171_0458118cd182f8b58c16e7c03f53edb4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 10. The progressive evolution observed in Model I-2 (conducted with five stages and surface processes), with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(e) The results of Model I-2 at total shortenings of 15 km (a), 19 km (b), 31 km (c), 33 km (d), or 35 km (e). T1–T5 denote thrust faults in the order of their formation.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0014-m_hubf866b07b778be6ad58892992afab537_713374_da6e7b84e784a14c761dad50ba3dd2b6.webp 400w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0014-m_hubf866b07b778be6ad58892992afab537_713374_6bfcbef29aba5d8ac44c72c725b96a24.webp 760w,
               /blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0014-m_hubf866b07b778be6ad58892992afab537_713374_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_2.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20221110/tect21806-fig-0014-m_hubf866b07b778be6ad58892992afab537_713374_da6e7b84e784a14c761dad50ba3dd2b6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;489&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 14. Comparison between the structural cross-section of the central Longmen Shan thrust belt and the results of Model I-2 (simulated with surface processes). (a) Structural profiles of the central Longmen Shan (modified from Jia et al., 2010) and the locations of the 2008 Mw 7.9 Wenchuan earthquake, the 2013 Mw 6.6 Lushan earthquake, and the 2020 Ms 5.1 Qingbaijiang earthquake. (b, c) Comparison of the structural profile and range front structure in Model I-2. (d, e) Comparison of the structural profile and foreland thrust belt in Model I-2. LQF, Longquan Fault. The location of (e) is shown in structural profile a1 in Figure 1.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on DEM simulations, we reveal the interaction between thrusting propagation and surface processes, and its influence on modern seismicity in the Longmen Shan fold-and-thrust belt and its adjacent WSFB. Based on our study results, we obtain the following conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DEM simulations without surface processes indicated that the fold-and-thrust belt developed in an in-sequence thrusting manner. In contrast, DEM simulations with surface processes revealed that the Longmen Shan fold-and-thrust belt developed in an out-of-sequence manner during the late Cenozoic. Starting at ∼30–20 Ma, rapid denudation processes occurred in the Longmen Shan hinterland, and the YBT and PGT Faults continued to be active. From ∼10 Ma to the present, large-scale propagation of denudation occurred from the Sichuan Basin toward the Tibetan Plateau, and tectonic activity retreated to the hinterland of Longmen Shan. Surface processes were relatively quiescent between these two stages, structural shortening propagated forward through the RFBT, and formed the Longquan Fault in the Sichuan basin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instrumental and historical earthquakes indicate that the frontal faults in the WSFB and the imbricate faults in the Longmen Shan hinterland region are simultaneously seismically active. We interpret that the activity of the Coulomb wedge of the Longmen Shan is related to the latest stage of surface process. Since ∼10 Ma, large and widespread propagation of erosion from the Sichuan Basin toward the eastern Tibet Plateau caused the Longmen Shan hinterland to enter a subcritical state. The reactivation of reverse faults in the hinterland enhanced the rapid uplift of the Longmen Shan and inhibited most of its slip lateral propagation to the foreland basin. The WSFB is currently in a critical state, with wedge slides occurring steadily along the shallow detachment, with the occurrence of frequent, small-moderate earthquakes in the frontal thrust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distribution of Mesozoic salt lakes in the interior of the Sichuan Basin influenced the location, rate, and structural style of thrust slip that propagated from the Longmen Shan hinterland to the foreland basin. Our simulations indicate that the front blind thrust of Longmen Shan range gradually connects the basal detachment and shallow detachment in foreland, and its position is controlled by the western boundary of the salt-lake. Results of comparative experiments show that fault slips from the hinterland of Longmen Shan entered the southwestern Sichuan basin extensively to form several thrust fault-related folds above shallow detachment. However, slip in the northern Longmen Shan was confined to the range front and did not propagate into the northwest Sichuan basin. This suggests that the structural variability along the strike in the Longmen Shan can be explained from the perspective of the internal factors of the Sichuan basin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research was supported by the National Key R&amp;amp;D Program of China (2021YFC3000604) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (42172232, 41702202, and 41927802). Numerical simulations were performed on the discrete element modeling software VBOX (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geovbox.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;www.geovbox.com&lt;/a&gt;). The authors thank Julia Morgan (Rice University) for generously sharing her discrete element code (RICEBAL v5.4) and post-processing scripts and algorithms, which have been used to process and display the model outputs presented in our modeling. The authors thank Dr. Chang-Sheng Li (East China University of Technology) for his suggestions in the numerical simulations. The numerical simulation of this study is performed on the computing facilities in the High-Performance Computing Center (HPCC) of Nanjing University. The authors thank Jonny Wu and Sharadha Sathiakumar for their constructive reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-availability-statement&#34;&gt;Data Availability Statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors used VBOX version 2.1 (C. Li et al., 2021; &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com/en/&lt;/a&gt;) for the discrete-element method (DEM) numerical simulations. Numerical simulations were conducted at the High-Performance Computing Center (HPCC), Nanjing University. The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework (Model I-1, no surface processes, &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/tz2qg;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/tz2qg;&lt;/a&gt; Model I-2, with surface processes, &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/pa9sy%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/pa9sy)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Li2019&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
李长圣, 2019. 基于离散元的褶皱冲断带构造变形定量分析与模拟. 博士论文. 南京: 南京大学.
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Liu-Zeng2008&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Liu-Zeng, J., Zhang, Z., Wen, L., Tapponnier, P., Sun, J., Xing, X., et al. (2009). Co-seismic ruptures of the 12 May 2008, Ms 8.0 Wenchuan earthquake, Sichuan: East–west crustal shortening on oblique, parallel thrusts along the eastern edge of Tibet. Earth and Planetary Science Letters, 286, 355–370. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2009.07.017
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Xu2009&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Xu, X., Wen, X., Yu, G., Chen, G., Klinger, Y., Hubbard, J., &amp; Shaw, J. (2009). Coseismic reverse- and oblique-slip surface faulting generated by the 2008 Mw 7.9 Wenchuan earthquake, China. Geology, 37, 515–518. https://doi.org/10.1130/G25462A.1
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Wang2012&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Wang, E., Kirby, E., Furlong, K. P., Van Soest, M., Xu, G., Shi, X., et al. (2012). Two-phase growth of high topography in eastern Tibet during the Cenozoic. Nature Geoscience, 5, 640–645. https://doi.org/10.1038/ngeo1538
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Richardson2008&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Richardson, N. J., Densmore, A. L., Seward, D., Fowler, A., Wipf, M., Ellis, M. A., et al. (2008). Extraordinary denudation in the Sichuan Basin: Insights from low-temperature thermochronology adjacent to the eastern margin of the Tibetan Plateau. Journal of Geophysical Research, 113, B04409. https://doi.org/10.1029/2006JB004739
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>龙门山新生代构造变形与模拟</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20200724/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20200724/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;课程回放&#34;&gt;课程回放&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;geovbox@哔哩哔哩　https://www.bilibili.com/video/BV1si4y137DX/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;时  间：2020年7月25日周六14:30-16:00&lt;br&gt;
Zoom会议ID：3059179425&lt;br&gt;
网址：https://zoom.com.cn/j/3059179425&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;构造网络论坛第十四期造山带构造演化龙门山&#34;&gt;构造网络论坛第十四期：造山带构造演化—龙门山&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;报告1: 龙门山符合逆冲带构造解析 中国地质大学（北京）颜丹平教授&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;报告2：龙门山新生代构造变形与模拟&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;报告人：&lt;a href=&#34;http://hyxy.hhu.edu.cn/2016/0622/c8640a104824/page.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;王毛毛&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 河海大学 海洋学院&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;内容简要：
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;青藏高原东缘：下地壳流VS上地壳缩短争论；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;龙门山褶皱冲断带新生代构造变形；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;新生代构造变形模拟的研究进展。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;报告中的数值模拟采用VBOX完成；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;模拟结果很好的解释了龙门山新生代前陆冲断带构造应变的差异性分布；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;实验设计及边界条件控制值得学习。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;构造物理模拟及数值模拟可以通过准确的边界条件和参数设置，定量的分析褶皱冲断带构造变形特征，是定量研究褶皱冲断带构造变形过程与变形机制的重要方法。与构造物理模拟相比，数值模拟可以得到更多的系统内部的信息（如应力、应变等） ，并且可重复性高，边界条件设置更容易(&lt;a href=&#34;#refer-anchor-1&#34;&gt;李长圣,2019&lt;/a&gt;)。二十世纪七十年代，Cundall and Strack(&lt;a href=&#34;#refer-anchor-1&#34;&gt;1979&lt;/a&gt;)提出了基于非连续介质力学的离散元法（Discrete Element Method，简称DEM） ，用于研究岩土体的各种力学行为。该方法将颗粒集合体模型视为若干离散单元的集合，允许颗粒间产生大位移，特别适合用于构造变形研究，是未来的构造变形研究的主要方向之一(&lt;a href=&#34;#refer-anchor-3&#34;&gt;Morgan,2015&lt;/a&gt;)。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;王毛毛副教授将在构造网络论坛中，介绍他的最新研究成果＂龙门山新生代构造变形与模拟＂。&lt;strong&gt;其中，数值模拟部分采用离散元数值模拟软件VBOX完成。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-海报&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;海报&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20200724/1_hud957a2a041187e16f1c790552469431b_92504_f95c207442192ce43358492bf38c1a2d.webp 400w,
               /blog/20200724/1_hud957a2a041187e16f1c790552469431b_92504_75b225184f91674695ba15dc45277459.webp 760w,
               /blog/20200724/1_hud957a2a041187e16f1c790552469431b_92504_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20200724/1_hud957a2a041187e16f1c790552469431b_92504_f95c207442192ce43358492bf38c1a2d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;547&#34;
               height=&#34;696&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      海报
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;致谢&#34;&gt;致谢&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;其中，应力应变分析代码修改自 RICE 大学Julia K. Morgan教授提供的计算脚本，在此感谢。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;参考文献&#34;&gt;参考文献&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-anchor-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
[李长圣 (2019) 基于离散元的褶皱冲断带构造变形定量分析与模拟. **博士论文**. 南京大学.](http://t.cn/Ai9ruJY5) **推荐下载** [最新修订版](https://pan.baidu.com/s/1s7qJXCUb2tP6jPkHixge6w) 提取码 `dgyc`  
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-anchor-2&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Cundall P A, Strack O D. 1979. A discrete numerical model for granular assemblies. Geotechnique, 29: 47-65.  
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-anchor-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
[Morgan JK (2015) Effects of cohesion on the structural and mechanical evolution of fold and thrust belts and contractional wedges: Discrete element simulations. **Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth** 120:3870-3896.](http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/2014JB011455/full)  
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
