<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>erosion | ZDEM官网</title>
    <link>https://geovbox.com/tag/erosion/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geovbox.com/tag/erosion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>erosion</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>zh-Hans</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geovbox.com/media/icon_hua235b20c26de23a006d4e436991121ab_912_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>erosion</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/tag/erosion/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Regional Erosion and Sedimentary Loading on Fault Activities in Active Fold-Thrust Belts</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210716/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210716/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;本文以龙门山褶皱冲断带为例，通过四个离散元数值模拟实验，揭示了：（1）剥蚀和沉积负载作用在活动褶皱冲断带新、老断层形成及其应力应变时空演化中具有重要影响作用；（2）研究区存在的差异性剥蚀和差异性同构造沉积负载作用可能是导致龙门山中段和南段形成差异性断裂活动及隆升的重要因素之一；（3）同构造沉积负载分布和发育（如成都平原的生长）对其腹部冲断楔中沿前缘断层面中的应力传播和应变汇聚有巨大的阻挡作用，导致应力汇聚主要发生在冲断楔体内部的主要活动断层上，进而在某种程度上解释了相比较龙门山北段，为什么其中段和南段更有利于地震的产生 &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-wu2021&#34;&gt;(Wu et al.,2021)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-wu2021&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
[Wu Z, Yin H, Li C, Yang X, Wang L, Wang F, Dong S and Jia D (2021) Influence of Regional Erosion and Sedimentary Loading on Fault Activities in Active Fold-Thrust Belts:
Insights From Discrete Element Simulation and the Southern and Central Longmen Shan Fold- Thrust Belt. Front. Earth Sci. 9:659682. doi: 10.3389/feart.2021.659682](https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.659682) 
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Influence of Regional Erosion and Sedimentary Loading on Fault Activities in Active Fold-Thrust Belts: Insights From Discrete Element Simulation and the Southern and Central Longmen Shan Fold-Thrust Belt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wu Z&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;, Yin H&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, Li C&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;, Yang X&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Wang L&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Wang F&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Dong S&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and Jia D&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State Key Laboratory of Nuclear Resources and Environment, East China University of Technology, Nanchang, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Sciences, East China University of Technology, Nanchang, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Sciences and Engineering, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four groups of discrete element models (DEMs) were set-up to simulate and analyze the influence of regional erosion and sedimentary loading on the formation and spatial-temporal evolution of faults in the southern and central Longmen Shan (LMS) active fold-thrust belt. The interior characteristics of faults in the southern and central LMS fold-thrust belt were also evaluated during the interaction of tectonic processes and surface processes according to the stress-strain analysis from DEM results. The results showed that synkinematic erosion promoted the reactivation of pre-existing faults in thrust wedges and also retarded the formation and development of new incipient faults in the pre-wedge regions. Meanwhile, synkinematic sedimentation also delayed the development of new incipient faults in the pre-wedge regions by promoting the development of thrust faults in the front of thrust wedges, causing these thrust wedges in supercritical stages with relatively narrow wedge lengths. According to these DEM results, we infer that: 1) The characteristics of erosion and sedimentation in the central and southern LMS have important influences on the activities of large faults which are extended into the deep detachment layer; 2) Besides differential erosion, the differential sedimentary loading may also be one of the important factors for the along-strike differential evolution of the LMS fold-thrust belt. This kind of differential deposition may lead to differential fault activity and uplift in the interior thrust wedge and pre-wedge region in the central and southern LMS; 3) Compared to the northern LMS, the central LMS and southern LMS is more conducive to the occurrence of earthquakes, because of synkinematic sedimentation (such as the growth of Chengdu plain) has a greater blocking effect on the stress propagation and strain convergence on the fault planes of front faults of an active thrust wedge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210716/figure1_hu8e275880bcc8aa2d700fea64bca65f5d_184003_6def6a369d5c493b991f4b03f861cad8.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210716/figure1_hu8e275880bcc8aa2d700fea64bca65f5d_184003_4827dfc75f9292f21cbaee8c8d1c8ec9.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210716/figure1_hu8e275880bcc8aa2d700fea64bca65f5d_184003_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210716/figure1_hu8e275880bcc8aa2d700fea64bca65f5d_184003_6def6a369d5c493b991f4b03f861cad8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;669&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;FIGURE 1 | Regional map of the LMS fold-thrust belt (A) and its geological structure map (B) (modified from [(Sun et al.,2016)](#refer-sun2016), Co-seismic rupture zones from [(Xu et al.,2009)](#refer-xu2009). (C) shows the thickness contour lines (100 m interval) of the Upper Pliocene and Quaternary (syntectonic sedimentary strata) beneath the Chengdu plain (cited from [(Li et al.,2018)](#refer-li2018). JTF, Jintang Fault; WLF, Wulong Fault; WMF, Wenxian-Maoxian Fault; SDF, Shuangshi-Dachuan Fault; PGF, Pengxian-Guanxian Fault; YBF, Yingxiu-Beichuan Fault; YAF, Yaan Fault; LQF, Longquanshan Fault; QCF, Qingchuan Fault; MJF, Minjiang Fault; HYF, Huya Fault; RFBT, Range Front Blind Thrust. &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210716/figure10_hufcdf19d454cb25bf5766cae5987f37bf_172946_0c6e7e343c413f9453571bdf60bfc10b.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210716/figure10_hufcdf19d454cb25bf5766cae5987f37bf_172946_80d7d93c62c4937687e61dcd62db0087.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210716/figure10_hufcdf19d454cb25bf5766cae5987f37bf_172946_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210716/figure10_hufcdf19d454cb25bf5766cae5987f37bf_172946_0c6e7e343c413f9453571bdf60bfc10b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;461&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; FIGURE 10 | Stress analysis of DEM simulations in Model 1 (A), Model 2 (B), Model 3 (C), and Model 4 (D). Mean stress (upper figure) and maximum shear stress (lower figure) are presented after every 2 units shortening. The main fault shapes (shades of black) are assigned to the stress maps.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210716/figure13_hu8883d115a79024024736e905a393e2f8_91185_5fdfe20770180dfc54b0a8a7486d3c9e.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210716/figure13_hu8883d115a79024024736e905a393e2f8_91185_33c63ac86654faa1d9d81bbec124c254.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210716/figure13_hu8883d115a79024024736e905a393e2f8_91185_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210716/figure13_hu8883d115a79024024736e905a393e2f8_91185_5fdfe20770180dfc54b0a8a7486d3c9e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;286&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;FIGURE 13 | The DEM results in this paper (A) and the conceptual model modified from Liu et al., 2020(B) present the occurrence of recess and salient in the front of thrust wedges.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-li2018&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Li, Z., Zhang, P., Zheng, W., Jia, D., Hubbard, J., Almeida, R., et al. (2018b). Oblique Thrusting and Strain Partitioning in the Longmen Shan Fold-Andthrust belt, Eastern Tibetan Plateau. J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth 123, 4431-4453. doi:10.1029/2018JB015529
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-sun2016&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Sun, C., Jia, D., Yin, H., Chen, Z., Li, Z., Shen, L., et al. (2016). Sandbox Modeling of Evolving Thrust Wedges with Different Preexisting Topographic Relief: Implications for the Longmen Shan Thrust belt, Eastern Tibet. J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth 121, 4591–4614. doi:10.1002/2016jb013013
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-xu2009&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Xu, X., Wen, X., Yu, G., Chen, G., Klinger, Y., Hubbard, J., et al. (2009). Coseismic Reverse- and Oblique-Slip Surface Faulting Generated by the 2008 Mw 7.9 Wenchuan Earthquake, China. Geology 37 (6), 515–518. doi:10.1130/g25462a.1
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>川西北双层滑脱体系构造变形过程离散元数值模拟</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;本文主要揭示双滑脱层模型在剥蚀和挤压条件下的构造演化过程。从腹陆端到挤压前缘，依次形成堆垛构造、被动顶板构造等，揭露
埋藏深部的隐伏薄皮构造样式，重塑新生代以来川西北剥蚀和挤压条件下的演化过程 &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-xu2021&#34;&gt;(Xu et al.,2021)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-xu2021&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
[Xu, W., Yin, H., Jia, D., **Li, C.**, Wang, W., Yang, G., He, W., Chen, Z., Ren, R., 2021. Structural Features and Evolution of the Northwestern Sichuan Basin: Insights From Discrete Numerical Simulations. Frontiers in Earth Science, 9:653395.](https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.653395) 
&lt;h4 id=&#34;题目&#34;&gt;题目&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural features and evolution of the northwestern Sichuan Basin Insights from discrete numerical simulations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenqiao Xu&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Hongwei Yin&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;*, Dong Jia&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Changsheng Li&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Wei Wang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Gengxiong Yang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,
Wanhui He&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Zhuxin Chen&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and Rong Ren&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Science and Engineering, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Science, East China University of Technology, Nanchang, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Institute of Petroleum Exploration and Development, Beijing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The northwestern Sichuan Basin has experienced Meso-Cenozoic intracontinental compressional tectonic processes and formed multi-detachment stratigraphic distribution of foreland basins and fold-thrust belts, which have caused complicated structural deformations in the deep buried layers. Rapid uplift with accelerated erosion and two sets of detachments in the Lower Triassic and Lower Cambrian controlled the multilevel deformation structure. We conducted discrete numerical simulations with double weak detachments and erosion under extrusion conditions in order to examine the mechanics and kinematics of the frontal piedmont zones of the NW Sichuan Basin. The following findings were made. (1) With continuous compression, the weak detachments promoted the decoupled and ladder-like deformation of the thrust belt, where the deformation above the slip layer extended further than it did below it. Rapid uplift and erosion at the thrust front contributed to the formation of a passive roof fault and a monocline in the upper layer, a series of forward and backward thin-skinned thrust-buried structures in the middle layer sandwiched between two weak detachments and stacking structures in the lower layer. (2) Erosion effectively prevents the deformation from propagating above the upper detachment, but can advance a horizontal transition in the deformation style generated within the middle brittle layer: from oblique and tight fault propagation folds to symmetrical, wide, and gentle detachment folds. (3) The model results consistent with tectonic deformation in the NW Sichuan Basin indicate a possible evolutionary mechanism under compression. There is hierarchical deformation of uncoordinated contraction controlled by the Lower Triassic and Early Cambrian weak layers, with the characteristics of the shallow monocline, the middle thin-skinned thrusts, and the deeper basement-involved folds. Continuous compression contributed a sequential pattern of steps as a whole, from the frontal piedmont zones to the foreland basin, autochthonous stacking thrusts, and the huge buried structure in the NW Sichuan Basin. During the Himalayan period, syntectonic erosion along with the uplifted thrust front maintained the development of a passive-roof duplex and a huge forward buried structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_b1f2e6b31556fe2dc3330c14e4ce11a0.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_8d004183b66203d9b6454a607446cb19.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/figure4-1_hu351b84480a4373bba1a4559171cfa7a8_266346_b1f2e6b31556fe2dc3330c14e4ce11a0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;567&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Modeled progress with two detachments due to the left-wall displacement &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_f4bc28b276feeb5d18b94ffeae5720fd.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_4d087576b96504b498433da025f941bb.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/figure6-1_hu98e5311d15f70333dfc94863fafa45e6_253436_f4bc28b276feeb5d18b94ffeae5720fd.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;569&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Modeled progress with two detachments and erosions due to the left-wall displacement&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_55290ad45df27a6e348506e07a0e9457.webp 400w,
               /blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_f0d4c75268a110c7c6ecb43e41bdcd6f.webp 760w,
               /blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20210329/figure8-2_hu50d0b5b781cba189957162cb38723640_101522_55290ad45df27a6e348506e07a0e9457.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;342&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Comparison of the slope angle versus shortening for the two models&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
