<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Master | ZDEM官网</title>
    <link>https://geovbox.com/en/category/master/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geovbox.com/en/category/master/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Master</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geovbox.com/media/icon_hua235b20c26de23a006d4e436991121ab_912_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Master</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/en/category/master/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Study on the Control Factors of Structural Deformation in the Southwestern Tianshan Piedmont Thrust Belt Based on Discrete Element Numerical Simulation</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20230315/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20230315/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;paper-download&#34;&gt;Paper Download：&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kns.cnki.net/kcms/detail/detail.aspx?filename=1022401115.nh&amp;amp;dbcode=CMFD&amp;amp;dbname=CMFD2022&amp;amp;v=vYLskAae-kRbfWamkMVYDbEC0D9yhdwvELrXuIsr1SwyGyi3UJFE11z7bBAEeGHb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wen Xin (2021). Study on the Control Factors of Structural Deformation in the Southwestern Tianshan Piedmont Thrust Belt: Based on Discrete Element Numerical Simulation. &lt;strong&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s Thesis&lt;/strong&gt;. Zhejiang University.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;title-study-on-the-control-factors-of-structural-deformation-in-the-southwestern-tianshan-piedmont-thrust-belt-based-on-discrete-element-numerical-simulation&#34;&gt;Title: Study on the Control Factors of Structural Deformation in the Southwestern Tianshan Piedmont Thrust Belt: Based on Discrete Element Numerical Simulation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;authorwen-xin&#34;&gt;Author:Wen Xin&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deformation of the eastern and western segments of the fold-thrust belt in the southwestern Tianshan Piedmont is significantly different. The Kashgar northern margin thrust belt in the western segment is characterized by the development of &amp;ldquo;stacked&amp;rdquo; structures and basement-involved thrust structures, while the adjacent Kalpin thrust belt in the eastern segment develops large-scale imbricate thin-skinned detachment structures. What factors control the deformation differences in the thrust belt? Based on seismic interpretation profiles, this thesis uses discrete element numerical simulation to analyze the influence of single-variable controlling factors on the deformation of the thrust belt. A total of 28 experiments were designed to investigate the effects of factors such as detachment layer strength, detachment layer position, caprock thickness, pre-existing faults, single and bidirectional compression, and bidirectional compression distance on the structural deformation of the fold-thrust belt in the southwestern Tianshan Piedmont. The following conclusions were drawn based on the experimental results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.The magnitude of the detachment layer&amp;rsquo;s cohesion plays an important controlling role in deformation. The cohesion of the detachment layer controls the ease with which faults beneath it can propagate upward. When the detachment layer has strong cohesion, it is easy for faults to break through the detachment layer along pre-existing weak zones, forming thrust nappe structures. When the detachment layer has weak cohesion, it will develop into a roof fault of the thrust system, hindering the upward propagation of pre-existing faults activated in the units below the detachment layer. A weak cohesion detachment layer can promote the deformation front to propagate faster and farther; it limits deformation to mainly occur in the units above the detachment layer, where triangular zones and pop-up structures are easily formed, and structural deformation in the units below the detachment layer is relatively weak. The smaller the cohesion of the detachment layer, the easier it is to form imbricate thin-skinned detachment structures; the thicker the overlying strata, the larger the scale and fewer the number of thrust sheets formed, and the greater the spacing between thrust sheets.
2.During single and bidirectional compression, stress and strain are mainly concentrated in weak zones such as detachment layers and faults, with stronger stress and strain near the compression end. The smaller the cohesion of the detachment layer, the easier it is for stress to propagate to distant locations. During close-range bidirectional compression, stress can propagate to the far end through the weak cohesion detachment layer, thereby affecting deformation at the far end. During long-range bidirectional compression, it does not affect deformation on the other side.
3.The Upper Cretaceous-Paleogene gypsum-salt detachment layer and pre-existing faults before the Cenozoic are the main controlling factors for the development of stacked deformation in the Kashgar northern margin thrust belt. At the same time, the northward compression of the Pamir arc tectonic belt has also affected the deformation style of the Kashgar northern margin thrust belt. The Paleogene gypsum-salt layer can serve as an effective detachment layer in the region. During compression, pre-existing faults from the pre-Cenozoic are successively activated and overlap to form a series of thrust sheets. The Upper Cretaceous-Paleogene gypsum-salt detachment layer acts as a roof fault, hindering the continued upward and southward propagation of deep faults beneath it, and forming &amp;ldquo;stacked&amp;rdquo; structures near the compression end. The Kashgar northern margin thrust belt is located in the Pamir and South Tianshan suture zone. Its southern front fault is affected by the northward thrusting of the Pamir arc tectonic belt, hindering the southward and upward breakthrough of the hidden thrust fault at the front edge of the Kashgar northern margin thrust belt. As a result, the Kashgar northern margin thrust belt does not form imbricate thin-skinned detachment structures similar to those in the Kalpin thrust belt.
4.The development of large-scale imbricate thin-skinned detachment structures in the Kalpin thrust belt is closely related to the Middle Cambrian gypsum-salt detachment layer and the thick Paleozoic sedimentary caprock. The development of thick Paleozoic and Cenozoic strata in the Kalpin area enhances the effectiveness of the Middle Cambrian gypsum-salt detachment layer as an effective weak cohesion detachment layer. During compression, a series of thrust sheets that converge downward into the Middle Cambrian detachment layer are formed, developing large-scale imbricate thin-skinned detachment structures. In addition, the Kalpin area is far from the West Kunlun-Pamir thrust belt, and its deformation is not affected by the northward compression of the West Kunlun-Pamir thrust belt. Within the Kalpin thrust belt, it is further divided into eastern and western segments bounded by the Piqiang fault. The Cambrian gypsum-mudstone-salt detachment layer in the western segment is buried deeper, with thicker overlying sedimentary strata. In contrast, the Cambrian gypsum-mudstone-salt detachment layer in the eastern segment is buried shallower, with relatively thinner overlying sedimentary strata. As a result, the thrust sheets in the western part of the Kalpin thrust belt are larger in scale, have greater spacing, and are fewer in number than those in the eastern part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;keywords-southwestern-tianshan-fold-and-thrust-belt-structural-deformation-controlling-factors-numerical-simulation&#34;&gt;Keywords: Southwestern Tianshan, fold-and-thrust belt, structural deformation, controlling factors, numerical simulation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter 1 Introduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter 2 Numerical Simulation Study of Thrust Belts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter 3 Regional Geological Overview&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter 4 Numerical Simulation Analysis of Deformation Controlling Factors in the Northern Kashgar Thrust Belt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter 5 Influence of Detachment Layers and Overlying Stratum Thickness on Deformation of the Kalpin Thrust Belt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter 6 Analysis of Controlling Factors for Deformation Differences between the Northern Kashgar Thrust Belt and the Kalpin Thrust Belt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter 7 Insights and Conclusions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;References&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20230315/ex3.6_huf3130f51138f61552c20cab4ebb1efea_682081_3108fd5e8a059d6bcaa8f2758222f691.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20230315/ex3.6_huf3130f51138f61552c20cab4ebb1efea_682081_c8e942359e7eb8d9f2162ab3b5e75650.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20230315/ex3.6_huf3130f51138f61552c20cab4ebb1efea_682081_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20230315/ex3.6_huf3130f51138f61552c20cab4ebb1efea_682081_3108fd5e8a059d6bcaa8f2758222f691.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;589&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Deformation-strain results from numerical simulation experiments on the Kalpin thrust belt&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translator: Ouyang Liujuan&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Element Post-processing Techniques and Their Applications in Structural Simulation (Preview)</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20221031/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20221031/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, we will invite Wei Huajing, a master&amp;rsquo;s student from Nanjing University, to present his research findings on discrete element post-processing, DEMpost. Teachers and students who are interested can download Wei Huajing&amp;rsquo;s master&amp;rsquo;s thesis for study first. The report time will be notified separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;thesis-download&#34;&gt;Thesis download&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kns.cnki.net/kcms/detail/detail.aspx?dbcode=CMFD&amp;amp;dbname=CMFDTEMP&amp;amp;filename=1021664929.nh&amp;amp;uniplatform=NZKPT&amp;amp;v=e5D04YZeOE6krJkFB%25mmd2BA6u8bMwzx%25mmd2FkyJjqC4HZrX6jLBHP44DVzv%25mmd2BkoQw0Xl8MjYl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HuajingWei&lt;/strong&gt; (2020) Discrete Element Post-processing Techniques and Their Applications in Structural Simulation. &lt;strong&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s Thesis&lt;/strong&gt;. Nanjing University.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;title-quantitative-analysis-and-simulation-of-structural-deformation-in-fold-thrust-belts-based-on-discrete-element-method&#34;&gt;Title: Quantitative Analysis and Simulation of Structural Deformation in Fold-Thrust Belts Based on Discrete Element Method&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;author-wei-huajing&#34;&gt;Author: Wei Huajing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;recommendation-reason&#34;&gt;Recommendation Reason&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discrete element post-processing program DEMpost developed in this paper can extract the stratum boundaries of particle systems, outline the scope of specific rock layers, and draw various cloud diagrams such as stress-strain, velocity, and displacement fields. It is an indispensable tool for quantitative research on structural deformation.
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-extract-stratum-boundaries&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Extract stratum boundaries&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20221031/1_hu3e07249610b6fafa1b3cb94eebbf8dd4_71443_c27444e6ac8e441be77f67c252f1d573.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20221031/1_hu3e07249610b6fafa1b3cb94eebbf8dd4_71443_e50f4f94ab716400512b44d2da8e3eb7.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20221031/1_hu3e07249610b6fafa1b3cb94eebbf8dd4_71443_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20221031/1_hu3e07249610b6fafa1b3cb94eebbf8dd4_71443_c27444e6ac8e441be77f67c252f1d573.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;694&#34;
               height=&#34;297&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Extract stratum boundaries
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-identify-salt-layer-extent&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Identify salt layer extent&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20221031/2_hu168127080e60d44f6b04f6e0a68bbfc3_158030_44feec6aed1e4602860c61752515b6c4.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20221031/2_hu168127080e60d44f6b04f6e0a68bbfc3_158030_e272bf7e89333e27af7101d6b5643536.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20221031/2_hu168127080e60d44f6b04f6e0a68bbfc3_158030_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20221031/2_hu168127080e60d44f6b04f6e0a68bbfc3_158030_44feec6aed1e4602860c61752515b6c4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;695&#34;
               height=&#34;433&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Identify salt layer extent
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-plot-stress-strain&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Plot stress-strain&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20221031/3_huccc3c28ff59037140879d19ea697d8f1_271793_6e9696fb21d73ecf9f7b06749ab6b194.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20221031/3_huccc3c28ff59037140879d19ea697d8f1_271793_d2e5095a78312b518f5014358c8b7038.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20221031/3_huccc3c28ff59037140879d19ea697d8f1_271793_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20221031/3_huccc3c28ff59037140879d19ea697d8f1_271793_6e9696fb21d73ecf9f7b06749ab6b194.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;700&#34;
               height=&#34;458&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Plot stress-strain
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discrete element method (DEM) is a numerical simulation technique that uses a microscopic particle system to simulate the deformation of macroscopic objects. It is widely applied in fields such as geotechnical engineering, structural simulation, and material transport. As an important means of quantitative structural research, structural numerical simulation establishes a connection between deformation mechanisms and geometric analysis of structures, overcoming the limitations of traditional structural analysis methods in the study of salt-bearing fold-thrust belts to a certain extent. DEM numerical simulation can present structural deformation and track the force and motion states of particles at each moment during the simulation, providing information on the stress-strain state and velocity-displacement field of the system. This allows for the study of small-scale deformations and fractures, enabling quantitative research on salt-bearing fold-thrust structures with significant scientific and economic value. Therefore, efficiently expressing the distribution of dynamic and kinematic characteristics in structural simulations has important application value. Based on literature research, algorithm design and development, computational examples, and structural numerical simulation experiments, this paper has completed the following work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.The literature review discusses the importance of multi-dimensional post-processing analysis for structural simulation: while structural deformation reflects the overall shape of the structure, the distribution of strain can reflect small-scale structural deformation in the model, the distribution of velocity fields can reveal the motion states of different structural units, and displacement gradients can provide a more detailed view of fracture distribution.
2.Designed and developed a post-processing calculation and visualization analysis module DEMpost adapted to the discrete element software YADE. The particle system is presented in the form of images through a rasterization algorithm, and the stress-strain and other characteristics of the particle system are presented in the form of images through an inverse distance weighted interpolation algorithm. The quality of these images is improved through other image processing algorithms. An association can be established between the structural deformation images in image form and the characteristic maps, facilitating the tracking of dynamic and kinematic characteristics of specific structural units during structural evolution.
3.Designed systematic discrete element numerical simulation experiments, analyzed the influence of common factors in salt-bearing fold-thrust belt structures, realized post-processing visualization of structural simulation based on DEMpost, and explored the mapping relationship between structural deformation and dynamic and kinematic characteristics. The simulation results show that the presence of a single gypsum-salt layer at the bottom causes stress-strain to rapidly propagate to the structural boundary, resulting in contraction and extrusion within the entire model and the development of a &amp;ldquo;box-like&amp;rdquo; structure; the presence of double gypsum-salt layers transforms rigid uplift associated with conjugate faults into a rheological fold structure, with stable stress-strain states within the gypsum-salt layers, and their influence on the structure is manifested as strain dispersion and triangular shear zones with a certain radiation range; pre-existing faults promote upward movement of the hanging wall along the fault, and factors such as the dip direction, dip angle, and scale of pre-existing faults affect the direction and distance of hanging wall movement, which in turn affects the range of deformation propagation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;keywords-discrete-element-method-post-processing-rasterization-spatial-interpolation-image-processing-structural-numerical-simulation-quantitative-analysis&#34;&gt;Keywords: discrete element method; post-processing; rasterization; spatial interpolation; image processing; structural numerical simulation; quantitative analysis&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.1 Quantitative Research on Fold-Thrust Belts and Structural Analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.2 Introduction to Discrete Element Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.3 Summary of This Paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.4 Research Methods and Technical Routes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.5 Workload of the Thesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algorithm Design and Development of Discrete Element Post-processing Techniques
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.1 Data Preprocessing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.2 Discrete Element Imaging
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.2.1 Structural Deformation Images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.2.2 Dynamic and Kinematic Characteristic Maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.3 Image Enhancement Processing
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.3.1 High-Frequency Noise Suppression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.3.2 Region Boundary Extraction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.3.2 System Outline Expression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.4 Summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational Examples and Advantages of Discrete Element Post-processing Techniques
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.1 Computational Examples of Discrete Element Post-processing Algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.2 Advantages of Discrete Element Post-processing Algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.3 Summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application of Discrete Element Post-processing Techniques in Salt-Bearing Fold-Thrust Belt Structural Simulation
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.1 Single Gypsum-Salt Layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.2 Double Gypsum-Salt Layers
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.2.1 Vertical Scale of Gypsum-Salt Layers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.2.2 Lateral Scale of Gypsum-Salt Layers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.2.3 Vertical Distribution of Gypsum-Salt Layers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.2.4 Lateral Distribution of Gypsum-Salt Layers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.3 Pre-existing Faults
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.3.1 Dip Direction of Pre-existing Faults&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.3.2 Dip Angle of Pre-existing Faults&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.3.3 Vertical Distribution of Pre-existing Faults&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.3.4 Lateral Distribution of Pre-existing Faults&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.3.5 Scale of Pre-existing Faults&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.4 Summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conclusions and Future Directions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5.1 Conclusions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5.2 Future Directions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translator: Ouyang Liujuan&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
