<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Journal_of_Structural_Geology | ZDEM官网</title>
    <link>https://geovbox.com/tag/journal_of_structural_geology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geovbox.com/tag/journal_of_structural_geology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Journal_of_Structural_Geology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>zh-Hans</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geovbox.com/media/icon_hua235b20c26de23a006d4e436991121ab_912_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Journal_of_Structural_Geology</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/tag/journal_of_structural_geology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>挤压环境下盐刺穿构造的形成机制：以塔里木盆地库车坳陷为例</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20240227/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20240227/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;刺穿构造的形成机理比隐刺穿构造更为复杂，目前对该问题的研究较少。本文在野外地质露头调查和地震资料精细解释的基础上，结合构造-沉积环境演化和生长地层特征，分析了库车坳陷盐刺穿构造的分布、几何形态和演化历史。在此基础上，通过离散元数值模拟实验，讨论了几种可能的因素对刺穿构造形成和演化过程的影响。结果表明：库车坳陷的盐刺穿构造主要发育在温苏古隆起北缘、却勒被动盐底辟和克拉苏基底先存断裂顶部。盐岩可直接穿透上覆地层，或通过断裂作用与围岩接触。生长地层特征表明，克拉苏地区的刺穿构造形成较早，温宿北缘的刺穿构造次之，却勒刺穿构造形成时间最晚。刺穿构造的演化可分为稳定期、弱挤压期和强挤压期三个阶段。在挤压环境下，仅仅依靠挤压应力，盐层很难形成刺穿构造。凸起的边缘、早期被动盐底辟、先存基底断裂顶部和沉积楔体的前缘，是刺穿构造发育的优先位置。古隆起的限制、基底断裂的再活化、早期被动盐丘的优先活动，以及造山带向盆地内部的进积作用，是刺穿构造发育的重要诱因。这些因素诱发刺穿构造的重要方式，是促进盐上地层的强裂冲断，从而为盐岩上涌提供通道。 &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-yang2024&#34;&gt;(Yang et al.,2024)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-yang2024&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;[**Yang, K.**, Qi, J., Shen, F., Sun, T., Duan, Z., Cui, M., ... &amp; Lv, J. (2024). Formation mechanism of salt piercement structures in a compressive environment: An example from the Kuqa depression, western China. **Journal of Structural Geology**, 178, 105005.](https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsg.2023.105005)
#### 题目
&lt;p&gt;Formation mechanism of salt piercement structures in a compressive environment: An example from the Kuqa depression, western China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keji Yang&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Jiafu Qi&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;, Fangle Shen&lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt;*,Liangwei Xu&lt;sup&gt;d&lt;/sup&gt;, Tong Sun&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, Zhanzhan Duan &lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt;, Meijuan Cui&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;，Li Peng&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;, Ji Lv&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a. Hebei Key Laboratory of Strategic Critical Mineral Resources, Hebei GEO University, Shijiazhuang 050031, China
b. State Key Laboratory of Petroleum Resources and Prospecting, China University of Petroleum, Changping, Beijing 102249, China
c. Huaxin College of Hebei GEO University, Shijiazhuang 050000, China
d. PetroChina Dagang Oilfield Exploration and Development Research Institute, Tianjin, 300280, China
e. Bureau of Geophysics Prospecting Inc., CNPC, Research Center of Geology, Zhuozhou 072750, China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The formation mechanism of piercement structures is more complex than that of concealed piercement structures, and little research has been conducted on this topic. In this work, based on surveys of field geological outcrops and detailed interpretation of seismic data, combined with the evolution of the tectonic-sedimentary environment and stratum growth characteristics, the geometry and evolutionary history of salt piercement structures in the Kuqa Depression are investigated. Through discrete element numerical simulation experiments, the influences of various factors on the formation and evolution of the piercement structure are discussed. The results show that the piercement structures in the Kuqa Depression are mainly developed in the northern margin of the Wensu paleohigh, the Quele passive salt diapir, and at the top of the Kelasu basement fault. The salt can directly pierce the overlying strata or contact the surrounding rock through faulting. The characteristics of the growth strata reveal that the Kelasu piercement structure formed first, followed by the Wenshu piercement structure, and the Quele piercement structure formed later. The evolution of the piercement structure can be divided into three stages: quiet, weak compression and strong compression. Relying solely on tectonic compressive stress, it is difficult for salt layer to form piercement structures. The most advantageous location for the development of the piercement structure in a compressive environment is in the margin of the paleohighs and low bulges and at the top of early passive salt diapirs and preexisting basement faults. The front of the sedimentary wedges is also a preferential location for the development of piercement structures. The barrier of the paleo-high, reactivation of the preexisting basement fault, priority activation of the early passive salt dome, and progradation of the sedimentary wedge from the orogenic belt to the basin interior are favorable factors inducing piercement structure formation. An important mechanism for controlling salt piercement is to promote strong thrusting in suprasalt strata, which provides a channel for salt upwelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr3_lrg_hu12ff4495c5a04844272905f0c1eacbd0_867522_37b1ec68b89f03c47fd86ec2cece128e.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr3_lrg_hu12ff4495c5a04844272905f0c1eacbd0_867522_69b8bf004adb0f700fa9c64dd5c52252.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr3_lrg_hu12ff4495c5a04844272905f0c1eacbd0_867522_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr3_lrg_hu12ff4495c5a04844272905f0c1eacbd0_867522_37b1ec68b89f03c47fd86ec2cece128e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;400px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt; Fig. 3. Numerical simulation experiment model setup: (a) basic model, (b) basement fault model, (c) preexisting salt dome model, and (d) paleo-high model. The initial setting of the progradation model is consistent with the basic model. &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr14_lrg_hu25e97a95526fe2ba9371137cda44de0b_1257713_c7902d2dd458be2cc857105d26ce7f32.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr14_lrg_hu25e97a95526fe2ba9371137cda44de0b_1257713_3db1e1b82862443f301404cc2e2d9399.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr14_lrg_hu25e97a95526fe2ba9371137cda44de0b_1257713_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240227/1-s2.0-S0191814123002225-gr14_lrg_hu25e97a95526fe2ba9371137cda44de0b_1257713_c7902d2dd458be2cc857105d26ce7f32.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;400px&#34;
               height=&#34;416&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt; Fig. 14. Comparisons of numerical simulation experimental results and seismic profiles crossing the piercement structures in the Kuqa depression. The results show that there is a significant similarity between the experimental results and seismic data.&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>多滑脱层对川东薄皮褶皱冲断带构造倾向的影响及其演化：来自数值模拟的启示</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/blog/20240214/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/blog/20240214/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;本文揭示了多滑脱层对川东薄皮褶皱冲断带构造倾向的影响及其演化。在川东薄皮褶皱构造中发育一系列后倾为主的滑脱褶皱，这在自然界中十分罕见，并且无法用经典临界楔体理论解释。本文设计了三个离散元数值模拟实验，探讨多滑脱对川东薄皮褶皱构造倾向和演化的影响。实验结果表明，多套滑脱层有利于形成反冲为主的对冲逆冲褶皱楔。上覆滑脱层的增加影响了褶皱楔的构造倾向和断层活动，实验结果在构造倾向和断层活动方面与川东褶皱带的结构相似，表明川东盆地内部薄弱层的分布对其影响不容忽视。基于以上模拟结果，本文提出了川东褶皱带耦合地球动力学过程的运动学模型。 &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-xu2024&#34;&gt;(Xu et al.,2024)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-xu2024&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;[**Xu, W.**, Yin, H.*, Zhao, S.,Zhang, C., Li, B., Jia, D., Li, C., Wang, W., 2024. Influence of multiple detachments on structural vergence and evolution of the thin-skinned fold-and-thrust belt in the eastern Sichuan Basin: Insights from numerical modeling,**Journal of Structural Geology**,180:105068.](https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsg.2024.105068)
#### 题目
&lt;p&gt;Influence of multiple detachments on structural vergence and evolution of the thin-skinned fold-and-thrust belt in the eastern Sichuan Basin: insights from numerical modeling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenqiao Xu&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Hongwei Yin&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;*,Shengxian Zhao&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Chenglin Zhang&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Bo Li&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Dong Jia&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,
Changsheng Li&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and Wei Wang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Science and Engineering, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shale Gas Institute of PetroChina Southwest Oil &amp;amp; Gasfield Company, Chengdu, China.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School of Earth Sciences, East China University of Technology, Nanchang, China.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;摘要&#34;&gt;摘要&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thin-skinned fold-and-thrust belt with multiple detachments in the eastern Sichuan Basin is characterized by a series of fault-detachment folds with a backward preferred structural vergence, which is rare in nature and can’t be explained well by the classic critically taper theory. Here, three discrete element simulations were conducted to study the influence of multiple detachments on the structural vergence and evolution of the eastern Sichuan thin-skinned fold and thrust belt. The experimental results reveal that multiple detachment layers affected the bulk mechanical strength and facilitated a dually vergent thrust wedge with a backward preferred structural vergence. The addition of intermediate detachment layers influences structural vergence and fault activity of thrust wedges. With the increase in intermediate weak layers, the preferred structural vergence of these model results progressively moved from forward to nearly symmetric and eventually to backward. These results exhibit first-order structural similarities to the structural vergence and fault activity in the eastern Sichuan fold and thrust belt, which indicates that the influence of the internal distribution of weak layers within the eastern Sichuan Basin should not be ignored. The limited Cambrian evaporite layer and the widespread Silurian shale and Lower-Middle Triassic evaporite layers had significant impacts on the deformation of the fold-and-thrust belt in the eastern Sichuan basin. Consequently, we propose a kinematic model for the coupled geodynamic processes of the eastern Sichuan fold-and-thrust belt. The framework of the eastern Sichuan Basin with a number of backward fault-detachment folds was formed by Mesozoic northwestward propagation, and Cenozoic eastward propagation reactivated the folding and thrusting. The Huayingshan fault was affected by the limited Cambrian evaporite layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240214/figure4-1_hud26fddf2a4ed6d8f25a729a0e739a4d1_162513_1b612deec6725cd54ab1301721fcf259.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240214/figure4-1_hud26fddf2a4ed6d8f25a729a0e739a4d1_162513_b227a078e1b7870d49c5fd2b6c87ca73.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240214/figure4-1_hud26fddf2a4ed6d8f25a729a0e739a4d1_162513_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240214/figure4-1_hud26fddf2a4ed6d8f25a729a0e739a4d1_162513_1b612deec6725cd54ab1301721fcf259.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;400px&#34;
               height=&#34;358&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Interpreted seismic section (a) and corresponding geological cross-sectional view (b) across the ESB (modified from Gu et al., 2021), and its position is shown in Figure 1b. The black arrows illustrate the positions of the three detachments. (c) Fault displacement statistics within the anticlines across the ESB. The fault displacements record the displacement of Permian layer in faults that at least connect the basal and top detachment layers. The displacements of minor faults between adjacent detachment layers have been disregarded. (d) The ratio of forethrust/backthrust displacements to the total displacements within the anticlines.  &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240214/figure6-1_hu6c0d8153b6a070b05dac0fb9c93e5e79_91737_7c132c77fcaa73f84d404498b67ff655.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240214/figure6-1_hu6c0d8153b6a070b05dac0fb9c93e5e79_91737_fa124703e0886081a2921e17ec1701df.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240214/figure6-1_hu6c0d8153b6a070b05dac0fb9c93e5e79_91737_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240214/figure6-1_hu6c0d8153b6a070b05dac0fb9c93e5e79_91737_7c132c77fcaa73f84d404498b67ff655.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;300px&#34;
               height=&#34;243&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt; Distribution of deformation (up) and velocity field (down) illustrated by (a) Model 1 with 10% BS, (b) Model 2 with 10% BS and (c) Model 3 with 10% BS and (d)14.3% BS, where γ is shear strain of the bulk overlying particles, Δt represents the period of time, Δu is the velocity between the upper surface and base, Δy represents the thickness of the particle layers, and Δx represents surface-bottom interface offset of particle motions. γ1-γ4 are measured by the angle of pink dash lines. Velocity schematic diagrams of back-vergent fold (e) and fore-vergent fold (f) with multiple detachment, which are interpreted from the squares in velocity fields of Model 3 with 10% BS and 14.3% BS, respectively.&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/20240214/figure8-2_hud9341578a4c7df5baaa9de89763ef8ac_44726_c9dcae72ffd1e38af78d9a93fb5bb214.webp 400w,
               /blog/20240214/figure8-2_hud9341578a4c7df5baaa9de89763ef8ac_44726_b20be928b08c60aa06ab52dcecc1511a.webp 760w,
               /blog/20240214/figure8-2_hud9341578a4c7df5baaa9de89763ef8ac_44726_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/blog/20240214/figure8-2_hud9341578a4c7df5baaa9de89763ef8ac_44726_c9dcae72ffd1e38af78d9a93fb5bb214.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;300px&#34;
               height=&#34;246&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Proposed kinematic model for the coupled geodynamic processes of the ESB. The evolution of ESB during (a, b) the Mesozoic intracontinental deformation at 100-80 Ma, and (c) Cenozoic eastward growth of the Tibetan Plateau at ~30Ma (modified from Tian et al., 2018). &lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
