<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Haoran Ma | ZDEM官网</title>
    <link>https://geovbox.com/en/authors/haoran-ma/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geovbox.com/en/authors/haoran-ma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Haoran Ma</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geovbox.com/media/icon_hua235b20c26de23a006d4e436991121ab_912_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Haoran Ma</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/en/authors/haoran-ma/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structural Control of Induced Seismicity in the Weiyuan Anticline, Southwestern Sichuan Foreland Thrust Belt, China(Tectonics)</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VBOX(ZDEM) script download：&lt;/strong&gt;
The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma, H., &amp;amp; Wang, M. (2025). Structural control of induced seismicity in the Weiyuan anticline, southwestern Sichuan foreland thrust belt, China. Tectonics, 44, e2024TC008617. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024TC008617&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2024TC008617&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;title&#34;&gt;title&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural Control of Induced Seismicity in the Weiyuan Anticline, Southwestern Sichuan Foreland Thrust Belt, China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;authors&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haoran Ma, Maomao Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institute of Tectonics and Geophysics, College of Oceanography, Hohai University, Nanjing, China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, the development of shale gas in the southwestern Sichuan foreland thrust belt, China, has led to a significant increase in induced seismicity, including one of the world&amp;rsquo;s largest hydraulic fracturing (HF)‐related induced earthquake (ML 5.4), occurring in the Weiyuan anticline. Here, we investigated the structural and mechanical evolution of the Weiyuan anticline and its relationship with HF‐induced earthquakes using seismic interpretation, the discrete‐element method (DEM), and three‐dimensional structural modeling. Interpretation of the seismic reflection profiles revealed a basement‐involved wedge structure and two west‐dipping multi‐bending thrust ramps in the basement. East of the Weiyuan anticline, extensive small‐ displacement thrust faults developed between the Cambrian and Silurian shale detachments in the sedimentary cover. DEM simulation showed that the structural wedge formed by the underlying blind thrust ramp and back thrust (BT) controlled the Weiyuan anticline formation. With increased shortening, the fault slip continued to propagate east of the Weiyuan anticline along the Cambrian detachment, leading to the development of
extensive thrust faults. 3‐D structural modeling showed that M &amp;gt; 4 induced earthquakes were primarily located on a BT in the structural wedge, while M &amp;lt; 4 events were distributed along the hydro‐fractured Silurian shale and Cambrian detachment. Densely developed thrust faults in the sedimentary cover connect the overpressured Silurian shale to the Cambrian detachment, promoting the downward diffusion of fluid pressure and favoring micro‐small M &amp;lt; 4 induced seismic events. This study provides new insights into the seismic hazard assessment of HF development in fold‐and‐thrust belts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_8fe5d28dadf6c4ce3732084825eec1ef.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_714782792c3053f8728b56061727783e.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/Figure1_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1509860_8fe5d28dadf6c4ce3732084825eec1ef.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;759&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 1. Topography map of the Longmen Shan and Sichuan Basin with major faults and cities. The red line indicates the location of seismic reflection profile PQ-92 in Fig. 5. The white pentagrams represent the MS 5.4 Weiyuan, MS 6.0 Luxian, MS 6.0 and 5.3 Changning respectively. The seismicity records from 1970 to 2014, and 2014 to 2020 are distinguished with grey and yellow circles, respectively. The earthquake data were obtained from the China Earthquake Networks Center, http://www.ceic.ac.cn/history in Chinese. 
 &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_dba48c0d4aca1af3b08fd66351c1b082.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_6de1cf103ebd262a0af4728d3c4ad55d.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/Figure5_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_2338025_dba48c0d4aca1af3b08fd66351c1b082.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;642&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; Figure 5. (a) Structural interpretation of seismic reflection profile PQ-92 across the region of the Weiyuan to Dengjingguan anticlines, with wells K7 and WH101 constraining the horizons, are shown. (b) Restoration results of deformed horizons from Weiyuan to Dengjingguan anticlines. The shortening of the base of the Jurassic layer in a representative structural profile is 2.5 km. The Cenozoic sedimentary strata within this area in the profile are absent. The profile is shown at 2X vertical exaggeration. BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_f7a1a4290c062fe8144a2b5fa2356cc0.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_3170092136c5ed84bcd1f699e407d9cb.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/Figure6_hu25d744f1b96eede93eb4b16e0082b6b6_789074_f7a1a4290c062fe8144a2b5fa2356cc0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;666&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 6. Schematic representation of the experimental setup. (a) The initial model setup contained homogeneous mechanical properties. (b) The contractional wedge model setup contained two-level  basal detachments and three detachments in sedimentary cover, the wedge point occurs within the basement. (c) The shallow thrust ramp merged with an east-dipping detachment fault at the wedge point. BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment.
&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_4b450c0abcc963648503ff7acbcda439.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_d414551ff007ee41336ad283d1493db5.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/Figure7_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1231821_4b450c0abcc963648503ff7acbcda439.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 7. Progressive evolution observed in homogeneous model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). F1–F5 denote thrust faults in the order of their formation. DTR: deep thrust ramp.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_908ae453918d28330f298b85e789c291.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_93a6c4d645139fd41e28f52cba3e6706.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/Figure8_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1430401_908ae453918d28330f298b85e789c291.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 8. Progressive evolution observed in contractional wedge model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). BT: back thrust; FT: fore thrust; STR: shallow thrust ramp; DTR: deep thrust ramp; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_35912b2b4e4322b897be09c884af18e4.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_a2b14f3a4947bbcd2e2206907926c078.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/Figure10_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_1483052_35912b2b4e4322b897be09c884af18e4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 10. Progressive evolution observed in the partitioned slipping wedge model, with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata. (a)–(d) The results of the model at total shortenings of 7 km (a), 10 km (b), 13 km (c), and 16 km (d). BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; STR: shallow thrust ramp; DTR: deep thrust ramp; D1: Middle Triassic detachment; D2: Lower Silurian detachment; D3: Mid-Upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_5b684210fb852c843ff7ebf0a0612d8b.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_00c5f07e4941f4d559ebf295cec6566f.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20250409/Figure11_huc2f095d956ac3e73b8db308a21e408b0_4116793_5b684210fb852c843ff7ebf0a0612d8b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;464&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Figure 11. Comparison between the structural cross-section of the Weiyuan to Kongtan anticlines and the result of the partitioned slipping wedge model. (a) Interpreted seismic profile in Figure 5. (b, c) The result of the partitioned slipping model when the shortening amount is 16 km, graph with distortional strains superimposed on the colored strata (b), graph only with distortional strains (c). BT: back thrust; PCD: pre-Cambrian detachment; D2: lower Silurian detachment; D3: mid-upper Cambrian detachment.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with structural interpretation, DEM simulations, and 3-D modeling, this study revealed the structure, kinematics, and mechanical evolution of a preexisting basement-involved structural wedge beneath the Weiyuan anticline and multiple detachments of the sedimentary cover in the southwestern Sichuan foreland fold-and-thrust belt, China, and discussed their influences on induced seismicity. Based on our study results, the following conclusions were drawn:
(1)The Weiyuan anticline is formed by a preexisting basement-involved contractional wedge consisting of a basal thrust ramp and a back thrust fault. East of the Weiyuan limb, the fault slip continued to propagate along the Cambrian detachment, contributing to the development of extensive low-displacement thrusts that cut through the Silurian shale detachment.
(2) The earthquakes induced in the Weiyuan block were primarily controlled by preexisting compressional basement-involved thrust structures and multi-level detachments in the sedimentary cover. The largest induced earthquake (2019 ML 5.2 event), along with other M &amp;gt; 4 earthquakes, occurred on BT within the basement-involved wedge structure.
(3) In the sedimentary cover, induced earthquakes (M &amp;lt; 4) primarily occurred between the Silurian shale and the middle–upper Cambrian shale detachments. Densely developed thrust faults connect the high-pore-pressure Silurian shale with Cambrian shale detachment, promoting the downward diffusion of pore pressure, which enhances the occurrence of induced earthquakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Editor‐in‐Chief Taylor Schildgen, Associate Editor Judith Hubbard, reviewer Andreas Plesch, and one anonymous reviewer for their comments and suggestions.This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (42172232 and 41702202) and National Key R&amp;amp;D Program of China (2021YFC3000604). Numerical simulations were performed on the discrete element modeling software VBOX (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.geovbox.com/en%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;www.geovbox.com/en)&lt;/a&gt;. The authors thank Prof. Julia Morgan from Rice University for generously sharing her discrete element code (RICEBAL v5.4) and post-processing scripts and algorithms, which have been used to process and display the model outputs presented in our modeling. The numerical simulation of this study is performed on the computing facilities in the High-Performance Computing Center (HPCC) of Nanjing University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-availability-statement&#34;&gt;Data Availability Statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used VBOX version 2.1 ( &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Li2021&#34;&gt;Li et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt; ; &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com/en/&lt;/a&gt;) for the discrete-element method (DEM) numerical simulations. The web site &lt;a href=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geovbox.com/en/&lt;/a&gt; provides manual and tutorial, examples, and references for VBOX version 2.1. The code for our DEM experiments can be obtained from Open Science Framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/)&lt;/a&gt;. The relocated seismicity data used in this study is provided by &lt;a href=&#34;#refer-Zi2023&#34;&gt;Zi et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;. The seismic reflection data, drilling wells, and structural maps were provided courtesy of the Southwest Oil and Gas Field Company, PetroChina. They cannot be released to the public. 3D models after time to depth conversion, including Middle-Upper Cambrian detachment, Lower Silurian detachment, and main faults, can also be obtained from Open Science Framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9hn74/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/9hn74/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Li2021&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Li, C., Yin, H., Wu, C., Zhang, Y., Zhang, J., Wu, Z., et al. (2021). Calibration of the Discrete Element Method and Modeling of Shortening Experiments . Frontiers in Earth Science, 9(May),1–12. 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.636512&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2021.636512&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-Zi2023&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Zi, J., Yang, H., Su, J., &amp; Chen, L. (2023). Structural constraints of induced earthquakes in the Weiyuan Shale Gas Field revealed by high-resolution body-wave tomography and earthquake relocation [Dataset]. Tectonophysics, 864(June), 230007. 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2023.230007&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2023.230007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Simulation of Differential Fault Evolution in Marginal Sea Basins A Case Study of the Pingbei Slope Zone in the Xihu Depression (Marine Geology &amp; Quaternary Geology)</title>
      <link>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20240720/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20240720/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper simulates the formation and evolution of landward-dipping and seaward-dipping faults through discrete element numerical simulation to explore the controlling factors of fault geometric development characteristics, providing insights and theoretical basis for the tectonic evolution mechanism of the East China Sea Basin and the formation of marginal sea basins&lt;a href=&#34;#refer-qu2024&#34;&gt;(Haoran Ma,2024)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refer-ma2024&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kns.cnki.net/kcms2/article/abstract?v=FqYZq-Q0wRQbYEmrDX8Mje95BMn_IPljoXMr0YcRIfyJ1IlbvIoNObYw-CP0JywPXVbQn7kkFLk4V50vOx_n1IQ6hfgsz_6iwt6NLSyQDXui7-EYgBwg0DTWZZnfCf94zdfADO88tHkG-JH5JL8v_aHlCTlvFu8NogMJqpOCjrQ=&amp;amp;uniplatform=NZKPT&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Haoran Ma,Jinbao Su,Maomao Wang,et al.Numerical Simulation of Differential Fault Evolution in Marginal Sea Basins: A Case Study of the Pingbei Slope Zone in the Xihu Depression[J].Marine Geology &amp;amp; Quaternary Geology,&lt;strong&gt;2024&lt;/strong&gt;,44(01):81-95.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;title&#34;&gt;Title&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerical Simulation of Differential Fault Evolution in Marginal Sea Basins: A Case Study of the Pingbei Slope Zone in the Xihu Depression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haoran Ma&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;，Jinbao Su&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;，Maomao Wang&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;，Peigang Ren&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;，Mingxuan Tan&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;College of Oceanography, Hohai University, Nanjing 210098, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science and Technology Development Branch, SINOPEC East China Petroleum Engineering Co., Ltd., Nanjing 210098, China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Mesozoic and Cenozoic basin formation of the East China Sea Shelf Basin, a large number of landward-dipping basin-controlling faults developed, and their development mode and formation evolution are significantly different from those of other marginal sea basins in East Asia. Previous studies focused on the migration characteristics of the East China Sea Shelf Basin but ignored the formation mechanism of differential fault evolution, lacking in-depth research on the controlling factors of fault development processes. The northern Pingbei Slope Zone of the Xihu Depression is a fault terrace area composed of seaward-dipping faults, while the southern part is a half-graben area composed of landward-dipping faults. The differential fault evolution indicates the basin formation process of the East China Sea Shelf Basin. This paper simulates the formation and evolution of landward-dipping and seaward-dipping faults through discrete element numerical simulation to explore the controlling factors of fault geometric development characteristics. The results show that lithological differences have a significant impact on the fault evolution of the slope zone. Rupture of strata with higher shear strength is prone to produce landward-dipping basin-controlling faults, while rocks with lower shear strength are prone to form seaward-dipping faults. The direction of stress is an important controlling factor for regional differential evolution. When the rock strength is the same, and the stress direction is opposite, the fault dip is also opposite. Numerous depression slopes developed during the basin formation process, but the slope is not the dominant factor in differential fault evolution. The differential evolution of the Pingbei Slope Zone and marginal sea basins may be caused by differences in basement strength or stress direction. This paper uses discrete element numerical simulation to study the differential evolution process of faults in the Pingbei Slope Zone, providing insights and theoretical basis for the tectonic evolution mechanism of the East China Sea Basin and the formation of marginal sea basins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt; &lt;/h5&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_5bc2434982aeee7b1c0a4dc209870410.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_96437ae548cd5dbfb5eb4b6e0ea63cae.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20240720/%E5%9B%BE5%E7%A6%BB%E6%95%A3%E5%85%83%E6%95%B0%E5%80%BC%E6%A8%A1%E6%8B%9F%E7%9A%84%E6%A8%A1%E5%9E%8B%E8%BE%B9%E7%95%8C%E6%9D%A1%E4%BB%B6_hu31bc73b36e8459a941783117d54b5cdb_40682_5bc2434982aeee7b1c0a4dc209870410.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Fig. 5 Model boundary conditions for discrete element numerical simulation&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_d62d474d710124a558a5c24713ef88f0.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_44ece86bcfa74109bb03de546ddde157.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_9830358d05bd3cb6516fed38c182e4d0.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20240720/_hu953eafef23284df0d09d80e35dd4cb43_245120_d62d474d710124a558a5c24713ef88f0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;647&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Fig. 6 Structural deformation, volumetric strain, and fault displacement statistics of Model 1&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_8e3d1def92cf36d80195deb4edebeeb7.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_a62b734bc9275684fcc745b39eef8bea.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_c66394e089a1068486f4d0e63fd7dab9.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20240720/_hue4235f0ccf87d4423247ffa8f68fb3c4_245896_8e3d1def92cf36d80195deb4edebeeb7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;636&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Fig. 7 Structural deformation, volumetric strain, and fault displacement statistics of Model 2&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_d5f0c724815ce6915e98e162ee39878b.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_f142e31b89995ba214593c5cdbbc0ae7.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_ab0fe22d4387d546c0a5b37bfe024bba.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20240720/_hu42765b7c952744d8cde128a0545bc2e1_227996_d5f0c724815ce6915e98e162ee39878b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;638&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Fig. 8 Structural deformation, volumetric strain, and fault displacement statistics of Model 3&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Structural%20deformation%20and%20volumetric%20strain%20of%20Model%204.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;600px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Fig. 9 Structural deformation and volumetric strain of Model 4&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_6d7ea7bebff6d77c264b5a866eb2a9dc.webp 400w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_002a855d965191df464c69e1672a27af.webp 760w,
               /en/blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_73ae9550489ccb35c3d8b0db918e1b25.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geovbox.com/en/blog/20240720/_hu97b00b11ea702fe50820e9abd4af76f1_241256_6d7ea7bebff6d77c264b5a866eb2a9dc.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600px&#34;
               height=&#34;645&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Fig. 10 Structural deformation, volumetric strain, and fault displacement statistics of Model 5&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rock strength and stress direction are the main factors affecting changes in fault dip. High-strength rock rupture produces faults opposite to the direction of extension, while low-strength rock rupture produces faults in the same direction as extension. Rocks with the same strength produce completely opposite main fault dips under the influence of opposite stress directions. The slope of the bedrock surface and the position of stress application are not the dominant factors in differential fault evolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The differential evolution of marginal sea basins in eastern China may be controlled by differences in basement strength and stress direction. The differential evolution of faults in the southern and northern Pingbei Slope Zone may be caused by differences in bedrock strength or stress direction. The landward-dipping basin-controlling faults in the East China Sea Shelf Basin may be caused by extensional stress towards the sea basin, while the fault development in the South China Sea margin basins may be the result of the combined effect of different stress directions on their basement. Differences in lithology and stress direction may lead to differential basin evolution, thereby affecting hydrocarbon migration and accumulation during the same period, but further research is still needed on the correlation between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numerical calculations in this paper were completed on the computing cluster of the High-Performance Computing Center of Nanjing University, and the numerical simulation experiments were completed using the discrete element numerical simulation software developed by Dr. Li Changsheng of East China University of Technology. The strain calculation code used in this paper was modified from scripts by Julia K Morgan and Thomas Fournier of Rice University, and we express our gratitude here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translator: Bao Xianjun&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
